<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached to the Honorable House of Commons; at their late solemne fast, December, 28. Wherein is described 1. The church her patience: 2. Her hope. In the exercise of both which graces, she is enabled to waite upon God in the way of his judgements: in which divers cases are propounded and resolved. That the soul sick of love, doth with more difficulty endure the absence of Christ, then the present evils of this world. By Thomas Valentine, Rector of Chalfont in Buckinghamshire. Published by order of that House.</title>
            <author>Valentine, Thomas, 1585 or 6-1665?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 131 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95864</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V26</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E86_32</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12382</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859274</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859274</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111346</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95864)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111346)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 15:E86[32])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached to the Honorable House of Commons; at their late solemne fast, December, 28. Wherein is described 1. The church her patience: 2. Her hope. In the exercise of both which graces, she is enabled to waite upon God in the way of his judgements: in which divers cases are propounded and resolved. That the soul sick of love, doth with more difficulty endure the absence of Christ, then the present evils of this world. By Thomas Valentine, Rector of Chalfont in Buckinghamshire. Published by order of that House.</title>
                  <author>Valentine, Thomas, 1585 or 6-1665?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 50 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Man, dwelling at the Swan in S. Pauls Chureh-yard [sic],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached at the late fast before the Honourable House of Commons.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "this sermon I heard preached; Jan: 28. 1642.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  History, (17th century)</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Zephaniah III, 8 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:111346:1"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Die Mercurij</hi> 28. December, 1642:</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is this day Ordered by the Houſe of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> that <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Valentine</hi> ſhall have thanks returned him from this Houſe, for the great pains he tooke in the <hi>Sermon</hi> he preached this day, at <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> Margarets</hi> in the Citie of <hi>VVeſtminſter,</hi> at the intreatie of this Houſe. And that he be deſired to <hi>Print</hi> his <hi>Sermon.</hi> And it is Order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that no man ſhall preſume to <hi>Print</hi> it, but he whom the ſaid <hi>M. Valentine</hi> ſhall authoriſe under his handwriting. And it is further Order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that Sir <hi>VVilliam Maſſam,</hi> a Member of this Houſe, ſhall returne the thanks to <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Valentine.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. Elſinge. Cler. Parl. D: Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <p>
               <hi>I appoint</hi> Samuel Man <hi>to Print my</hi> Sermon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentine.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111346:1"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED AT THE LATE FAST Before the Honorable Houſe of COMMONS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ZEPH. 3.8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Wait upon me, ſaith the Lord, untill the day that I riſe up to the prey, for my determination is to gather the Nations that I may aſſemble the kingdoms, to powre upon them mine indignation, even all my fierce anger, for all the earth ſhall be filled with the fire of my jealouſie.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T appears by the next verſe, that a full Reformation was promiſed. For God tels them, he will give them a pure language, or a pure lip. They ſhould have, and ſpeak of nothing but pure and holy ordinances, the names of Idols, and idolatrous worſhip, ſhould be baniſhed and quite forgotten: It is alſo as clear by the latter part of this text, that a great deſolation was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the enemies of the Church: till both theſe be done, we muſt wait. A dutie of much difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, for when we have ſtrong deſires, uſually they are unrulie:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111346:2"/> and if we have enemies, naturally we are deſirous of their ſpeedie downfall. We take up <hi>Jeremies</hi> expreſſion, but few have his ſpirit, <hi>Jer.</hi> 11.20. <hi>Let me ſee thy vengeance upon my enemies:</hi> and are too like him in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> who ſaid to his adverſarie, <hi>I doubt not but thou ſhalt pay for it, but I am afraid I ſhall not ſee it.</hi> Leſt we ſhould be tranſported with theſe deſires, and grow impatient, God gives a charge to wait his leaſure. There is a day ſet, a time prefixed, beyond which Gods patience to evill men ſhall not extend it ſelf. I will in due time (ſaith God) ariſe like a Lion to the prey, I will ſpoil them, that ſpoil you, I will teare them in peeces, and they ſhall never recover their ſtrength any more.</p>
            <p>When this propheſie took effect, and what age it pointed at, is not determined by Interpreters, ſome think it was fulfill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Joſiah</hi> his time, becauſe this Prophet lived in the time of his reigne; ſo <hi>Ribera,</hi> and <hi>Druſius</hi> conjecture, and it might be ſo, becauſe <hi>Joſiah</hi> did not begin his Reformation till the twelfth yeer of his reigne, 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 24.3. Others think it was meant of the reſtauration of the Church after the captivitie, becauſe in <hi>Joſiah</hi> his time though there was a Reformation, yet no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to the enemies thereof.</p>
            <p>Others refer it to the times of the Goſpel, becauſe the calling of the Gentiles is mentioned, and alſo that conſent of ſerving God with one ſhoulder, was verified in <hi>Act.</hi> 2.46. <hi>They ſerved the Lord</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>with one accord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others refer it to the end of the world, and they make this Scripture and that of <hi>Joel</hi> 3.16. to be meant of the laſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: becauſe fire, and indignation, and all Gods fierce anger ſhall then be powred out to the full: And the phraſes uſed in <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.29. of the latter end of the world, do agree to this, and that of <hi>Joel</hi> and the multitude here and there mentioned, have made them think it could be no other. The notation of the name <hi>Jehoſaphat, Haiah and ſaphat, ſit indicium,</hi> the Papiſts beleeve that the vallie of <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi> ſhould be the place of judgement.</p>
            <p>But let wiſe men conſider, whether to make a valley ſo ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacious, as to hold all the people, that have lived from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world to the end, be not an opinion ſo impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, as needs no confutation. All that which can be inferred,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111346:2"/> is that the laſt judgement, and great temporall judgements, hold a ſutableneſſe, and correſpondencie one with another. For the time of this propheſie I ſhall not meddle with in this exerciſe.</p>
            <p>In the text obſerve, <list>
                  <item>1 A dutie which is commanded.</item>
                  <item>2 A motive whereby it is enforced.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>In the former obſerve, <list>
                  <item>1 The dutie it ſelf, Wait,</item>
                  <item>2 The object, upon me, ſaith the Lord.</item>
                  <item>3 The time, how long? untill the day that I riſe to the prey.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond (which is a commination againſt the enemies) obſerve: <list>
                  <item>1 The generalitie of it, nations, kingdoms, and the whole earth.</item>
                  <item>2 The certaintie of it, I am determined to do it, ſaith God.</item>
                  <item>3 The terribleneſſe of it, ſet out, in Gods indignation, all his fierce anger, and the fire of his jealouſie.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>If you look upon the beginning of this Chapter, from the firſt verſe to this text, you may ſee that the Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth were exceedingly corrupted. For ver. 3. it is ſaid, that the Princes were as roaring Lions, the Judges were as the evening wolves, they knaw not the bones till the morning: ſuch as ſhould protect and defend them, did ſpoil and devoure them. The Prieſts and Prophets that ſhould offer ſacrifice for them, and inſtruct them, were vain light perſons, and did pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute the ſanctuatie, and wreſt the Law. Theſe that were ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, bred and born in their own kingdom, as well as thoſe abroad, are threatned, and it is evident that the Churches Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and her enemies deſolation, muſt come together: and till both theſe be done, we are commanded to wait. So that you ſee what is to be the ſubject of our enſuing diſcourſe; and if you will have it in an obſervation, it is this:</p>
            <p>Though wicked men be not puniſhed and pulled down, and though the Church be not reformed, ſo ſoon as we could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, yet we muſt wait upon God till he do it.</p>
            <p>To wait, is cheerfully to expect the fulfilling of all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes wherein lies the Churches good: and the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all the threatnings, that reſpect the enemies: And if to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111346:3"/> this, we adde the manner, then to wait is ſo attend upon God, as that the want of any bleſſing deſired, become no hindrance, either to our affections or religious actions; For if either be, it is not the waiting God accepts.</p>
            <p>In waiting 3. things,</p>
            <p n="1">1 There is a want of a bleſſing, elſe there were no need of waiting; It is the ſervice of a defective ſtate, when all ſhall be compleat in heaven, there will be no need of waiting, we ſhall ſee God, and injoy him, and in him all things. We ſhall have all our deſires granted, but in this world we are under many preſſures, and want many bleſſings, and muſt wait.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In this time of our want, yet we muſt not cool in our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, but muſt love God, and rejoyce in him, elſe we are mercenarie, it we ſhould be deprived of all that is dear unto us, <hi>If the fig-tree ſhould not bloſſome, neither ſhall fruit be in the vines: the labour of the olive ſhould fail, and the fields ſhall yeeld no meat, the flock ſhall be cut off from the fold, and there ſhould be no heard in the ſtalls yet will I reioyce in the Lord, I will ioy in the God of my ſalvation.</hi> Habba. 3.17, 18.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We muſt not leave work, nor give over our ſervice, but wait for a bleſſing: if ſucceſſe follow not, yet we muſt go on; we have principles that will carrie us through all diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Such as wait, ſecond what they have done, they pray over their prayers again: but ſuch as will not wait, they relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh their work, and deſert the cauſe, they recant and recall what they have done. It ſeems to me to be the preſent dutie that God requires of us in this Land, it is the leſſon of the time, we have an expectation of evill mens juſt puniſhment, and the reformation of our kingdom: both of them, and all things elſe ſeem to be at a ſtand, the people both in Citie and Countrey, are troubled. Their eager deſires after both have made them impatient: and as <hi>Naaman</hi> in the peeviſhneſſe of his ſpirit, ſpake of the manner and means of the cure of his le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie (being diſcontented with the way that God had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed) ſo the people ſay, we thought before this time our peace and Religion would have been ſetled, we thought upon ſuch a day, and in ſuch a place ſo great things would have been done, that our troubles would have been ended. The minds of moſt men are like the troubled waters, and which is
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111346:3"/> worſe, the mud is ſtirred, and if men give way to their paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they will be like the raging Sea, and caſt up dirt. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my text is a meſſage to them, God ſaith, have patience a while, and wait: I will in due time ariſe to the prey, I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy your enemies, and reform your Kingdom. And though the vapours and miſts are below, do not reach to the higheſt Region of the aire: yet men of higheſt rank, are but men, and are ſubject to paſſions as well as others: therefore you (the Worthies of our Land) may poſſibly be a little wearie, and faint in your minds, I am ſure that as your pains and trials are greater; ſo your temptations, and diſcouragements are anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able: therefore my text is a meſſage to you, wait upon God till he ſecond your pious endeavours with happie ſucceſſe; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult and wait, work and wait, pray and wait, abate not in your zeal, deſiſt not in your work: but to what ever you do, adde this dutie of waiting, and God will make you the happie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of the kingdoms good.</p>
            <p>If any man ſhould fall off (which God forbid) from his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer zeal, or purpoſe, or proteſtation, let him with this text, read that in <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.38. <hi>He that draws back, my ſoul ſhall have no pleaſure in him, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a double work for every waiter; 1. To want the good he is in expectation of. 2. To bear that evill that befalls him in the meane ſpace; and our waiting conſiſts in our pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, for that bears evill: and in our hope, for that expects good. And <hi>Junius</hi> in his ſhort annotations upon this text, ſums up briefly what others ſpeak more largely, patiently beare your captivitie (namely, in Babylon) and cheerfully expect your deliverance, and then ye wait upon God.</p>
            <p>The Hebrew word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cu,</hi> rendred by <hi>Pagine</hi> and <hi>Buxtorf. Expectate me preſtolamini me,</hi> expect me, or attend me. The ſame is uſed, <hi>Job</hi> 32.4. <hi>Elibu expectavit Jobum: Expected when Job would make an end. Pſal.</hi> 62.1. Truly my ſoule waiteth upon God. The word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>umijah,</hi> of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>duum ſiluit: My ſoul keepeth ſilence to God.</hi> And the word is uſed in <hi>Pſ.</hi> 37.7. <hi>reſt in God.</hi> He that waits, reſts; and he that is impatient is reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe. And in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40 1. <hi>I waited patiently; David</hi> bears the fruits of <hi>Sauls</hi> malice, and yet he looks after the Kingdom; if our deſires and hopes be deaded, and dulled: we wait not,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111346:4"/> though we patiently bear evill, and if we have ſtrong deſires, and are impatient under croſſes, we are wanting in this dutie, and therefore we muſt ſpeak to them ſeverally.</p>
            <p>Patiently to bear evill,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Church her patience.</note>Is a quiet ſilent temper of ſoul, whereby we ſubmit to God in all our croſſes. There was never more need of patience then in our dayes, the whole Kingdome ſpeaks in that language; <hi>Jer.</hi> 14. <hi>We looked for healing, and behold trouble:</hi> we expected Reformation, and behold deſolation. We muſt patiently bear one, and yet cheerfully expect the other. Many ſay, <hi>This evill is of the Lord, and why ſhould I wait any longer?</hi> but good hearts reſolve ſtill with them in Iſa. 8.17. <hi>I will wait upon the Lord who hath hid his face from the houſe of Jacob, and I will yet look for him.</hi> There is a paſſive perfection, as well as an active in a Chriſtian; God diſpoſeth of our imployment, ſometimes we muſt be do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſometimes we muſt ſuffer: ſome are excellently active, but not ſo commendably paſſive: they are quick and nimble in action, but when croſſes come they are weak, and cannot wait. The Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and the Latine <hi>patientia,</hi> tells us we muſt ſuffer. And it may be we ſhall have ſickneſſe, and ſore diſeaſes in our bodies, great loſſes in our eſtates, we may be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed into a farre Countrey, or impriſoned in ſome dark dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, we may be blemiſhed in our reputation, by ſoule ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, we may be betrayed by falſe friends, and purſued by cruell enemies: we may have calamities in our life, and torments in our death, there is no affliction for kind, or continuance, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, that the ſervants of God are exempted from, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they had need to be fitted to ſuffer. And the word uſed <hi>Galat.</hi> 5.22. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is long ſuffering, we cannot tell how long we ſhall ſuffer; It is not fit we ſhould know it before-hand: for if it were very long, we ſhould be out of heart, and out of hope to hold out; If it were ſhort, that were not praiſe worthy. Therefore God keeps us in ſuſpence, and ſpeaks indefinitely of the time, wait upon me untill I riſe to the prey. We muſt bring forth fruit, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>in patience, Luk.</hi> 8.15. the word in the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of it ſignifies to abide; we muſt abide in our work, and in a religious temper of ſpirit, and not be beaten out by afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: or delay of bleſſings. If we do well, and ſuffer well, if <hi>patience have her perfect work, we are intire and lack nothing: Jam.</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:111346:4"/> 1.4. Our bleſſed Saviour was ſometimes in action, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in his paſſion: his active and paſſive obedience made him a compleat Mediatour. And thy active and paſſive graces will make thee a compleat Chriſtian. There is no croſſe can endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger him that hath a quiet ſpirit, for he ſtands <hi>firm like a moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, Pſal.</hi> 125.1. the ſtormes may ariſe, and the winds blow, the mountain ſtands firm for all this. But if there be an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, that will ſhake it: Enemies may traduce thee, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe thee, and calamities like a ſtorm may fall upon thy head: and theſe may be born; but if thy ſpirit be impatient, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet, that's an earthquake in thy ſoul, and will do thee more hurt then the malice of thy worſt adverſarie. There is no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable living in this world without patience, for the leaſt trouble puts us out of frame, but the grace of patience doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover us, and if it can prevail, keeps the mind quiet. <hi>Aquinas</hi> makes it the root of all graces: but his explication muſt be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in, <hi>Non cauſando</hi> or <hi>conſervando, ſed removendo prohibens: It is the let removing cauſe.</hi> For trouble comes, and would hinder us in our love, and joy, and hope, and confidence in God; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience bears all, and quiets the ſoul, and in ſo doing removes the evill of the trouble, that it becomes no impediment to our graces. It was a prettie conceit of the Poet,<note place="margin">Aqui. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> ſecundae, q. <hi>56.</hi> art. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> that made everie vertue without patience to be as a widow, for as ſhe wants half of her ſtrength, and wiſdom and counſell: ſo thy faith, and love, and hope, are but weak, and patience guards them. Therefore in <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.12. <hi>Faith and patience</hi> are coupled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. <hi>Hope, and patience, and comfort</hi> are united. We are ſaid <hi>to run the race that is ſet before us with patience. Heb.</hi> 12.1. It ſeems a kind of contradiction to run with patience; for run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is active, and patience is paſſive, and therefore one is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from the other, if not oppoſite; but he that runs, and wants patience, will never get to the end of the race. For in the race of Gods Commandments, men have ſoule play: one comes and rails on him for his zeal, for running ſo faſt, when he thinks himſelf too ſlow; another gives him a blowe and ſtrikes him down, and up he gets and runs again. And whereas everie man will make roome, and give way to him that is in a race: he that runs to heavenward, many will ſtand in his way and ſtop him, in all which he had need of patience: And we
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111346:5"/> may put it among the cardinall graces, which are ſo called <hi>à Cardine,</hi> for as <hi>Janua ſine cardine, as a doore without hinges cannot be beneficiall to ſhut out the cold, or any thing elſe that will offend him:</hi> ſo is a man without patience, every thing will offend him; what is a wiſe man, a zealous man without patience? he will beare nothing, ſuffer nothing, and then he will do no great good I have often marvelled, why ſo little is written on this ſubject: we are beholding to <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and <hi>Tertullian</hi> for two ſhort Tractates of patience, others both ancient and modern, ſpeak of it for the moſt part as other theames that come in their way; we have need to preach it, and practiſe it, there is a daily uſe of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Patience is a ſilent temper of ſpirit; in oppoſition to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience, which is either ſecretly murmuring and repining, or elſe openly clamorous: ſometimes cauſing wrangling diſputes not onely with men, but God himſelf; as we ſee in <hi>Jonah, cap.</hi> 4.1.4. ſometimes unjuſt complaints in a higher degree, as we ſee in the Iſraelites, who did chide with <hi>Moſes,</hi> when they wanted water or any thing elſe: <hi>Numb.</hi> 20.3.4. <hi>Would God we had died when our brethren died.</hi> They died in their ſin, for they luſted, and while the meat was between their teeth, the wrath of God was kindled againſt them, and he ſmote the people with a great plague,<note place="margin">Num. 11.33.</note> a fearfull death was inflicted, and yet they are ſo farre from being reſtrained thereby, that they break out again into intemperate language, that heaven and earth rings again, and they fill the eares of God and man with their clamours; when they were in Egypt they groaned, when they were come out they wiſhed themſelves there again: when they want ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries they murmure, and cannot wait. They had the mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous manifeſtation of Gods power and goodneſſe in the daily ſupply of their wants: and yet they will not truſt him, but in the perverſeneſſe of their impatient ſpirit, wiſh that either they had ſtayed in Egypt, or died with their brethren. I would the like did not appear in our Land at this day; many are readie to ſay, would God we had not looked after a Reformation, that we had never thought of any alteration, then we had not known theſe troubles, and dangers, and this great expence of money. It may be theſe will do, as they did with <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron, Exod.</hi> 5.21.23. lay the blame on them whom God
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111346:5"/> uſed as inſtruments of their good, and ſay, <hi>You have made our ſavour to be abhorred in the eyes of Pharaoh, and his ſervants.</hi> And if you will know the cauſe of theſe diſtempers, one among the reſt is, they like not that way, nor thoſe Ordinances which others pray for, and wait for: It is with them as with the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that were to come out of Babylon, <hi>Though libertie to return was granted by Cyrus:</hi> yet many ſtayed behind, of whom there is mention made, in 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 4.23. <hi>theſe were potters, and thoſe that dwelt amongſt plants and hedges, there they dwelt with the king for his work.</hi> They dwelt with the King of Babylon, their em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment was meane, they made pots, they were potters, their habitation was anſwerable: they dwelt under hedges, they were poore ſpirited men, the baſe brood of their degenerated forefathers: for they made brick in Egypt, and would have been contented with that bondage, and drudgerie; ſo theſe would rather make pots in Babylon, and dwell under hedges, then go after their freedome in Sion. They are branded in the words before, for though the latter end of verſe 22. be tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>theſe are ancient things,</hi> yet <hi>Junius</hi> renders it, theſe <hi>are res ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoletae,</hi> things worn out and forgotten; and indeed they deſerve to be forgotten. But let us remember them, as theſe worthie Jews did, whoſe ſpirit God had touched to go on to build the Temple at Jeruſalem, they pray for them in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.4. <hi>Turn our captivitie, as the ſtreams in the South.</hi> It was penned upon this Occaſion, and that prayer on purpoſe made in behalfe of theſe Jews that ſtayed behind in Babylon. They take them to be their captives, being but obliged unto them by a nationall bond. So let us pray for thoſe of our Nation, that are loath to come out of Babylon. But let us not wonder at the ſtirs, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions in our Land, the ſame cauſes have produced the like effects in former ages; nor let the backwardneſſe of thoſe that keep off, diſcourage you (the worthie Inſtruments of God) from going on to build the Temple, and reform the Kingdom; but let your forwardneſſe, bring them on by the example of thoſe noble Jews alreadie mentioned. If the grace of patience did prevail, and we were willing to wait upon God, theſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers would be quieted, and put to ſilence. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.28. <hi>He ſitteth alone, and keepeth ſilence, becauſe he hath born it upon him. He putteth his mouth in the duſt if there may be hope.</hi> There is the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111346:6"/> poſiture of a patient man, he ſitteth alone, and retires himſelf, till God will look on him, and grant him his deſires, in the meane time he will not charge God fooliſhly, he keepeth ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, he will bend himſelf to bear his affliction, and if after much waiting, God would give him hope to be delivered, he in his familie would kiſſe the duſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> had many enemies, <hi>that ſpake miſchievous things againſt him, and laid ſnares for him, Pſal.</hi> 38.12.13. <hi>but he was as a deafe man that hard not, and as a dumbe man that openeth not his mouth.</hi> He wanted neither courage, nor wiſdom, he had a ſtirring ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, a working head, he was ſencible of their wrongs, he knew himſelf innocent, his adverſaries malicious: his thoughts muſt needs be troubled, and yet he breaks not out, but is ſilent, and it was becauſe he had the uſe, and exerciſe of his patience. This ſhews the power and efficacie of his grace, it rules when all is in an uprore in the ſoul, when unrulie paſſions fall into a kind of mutinie, then patience makes them hold their peace; and be ſilent. We may ſuppoſe patience in the ſoul, to be as the Town Clark in Epheſus, <hi>Acts</hi> 19 35. <hi>The City was in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, and there was a cry for two houres together.</hi> He comes and appeaſeth the multitude:<note place="margin">Verſ. 36.</note> by alleagiance, 1. ver. 36. <hi>Ye ought to do nothing raſhly;</hi> 2. <hi>If Dimetrius and the Craftſmen have any thing to ſay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 38. Ver. 40.</note> 
               <hi>the Law is open, and there are diſputes.</hi> 3. <hi>We are in danger of this dayes ſedition.</hi> Juſt ſo comes in patience, when wrongs and injuries are offered; bleſſings are delayed, the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is put out of frame, and readie to break out; then it mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, and ſaith, you ſhould do nothing raſhly. Paſſion is raſh, but patience is adviſed, and diſcreet. And next, the Law is open, the eares of God are open to receive your complaints if they be tendred to him in a religious way, and he will right you; for he is the God, to whom vengeance belongeth. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it ſaith thou art in danger of Gods diſpleaſure, by this daies impatience: and ſo it ſends away theſe mutinous thoughts, as he did the multitude: and makes the heart to yeeld to God, and it cauſeth a man to lay his hand upon his mouth, and become dumbe. And ſo patience makes a dumbe ſhew: but it is a verie good one, for it makes him like our bleſſed Saviour, <hi>Who was dumbe before the ſhearer, and opened not his mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſeeing patience, is a paſſive, quiet, ſilent temper of ſoul:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111346:6"/> it may be demanded, and a caſe may be put; whether all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of our ſorrow, in time of afflictions, be fruites of Impatience? And oppoſite to the duty of waiting? And what we may thinke of thoſe places in <hi>Jſa.</hi> 59.11. <hi>Wee roare like Beares, and mourne like Doves.</hi> And alſo, <hi>Jſa.</hi> 52.5. <hi>They that rule over them, make them to howle?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For anſwer, We muſt conſider a man in a three-fold ſtate: Firſt, in his nature common with other Creatures; the <hi>Oxe lowes,</hi> the <hi>Sheepe bleats,</hi> the <hi>Ravens cry:</hi> And man, if he be hurt, and wounded, or wronged, and oppreſſed, he hath ſenſe and reaſon, and ſhould be ſenſible of the Evils that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall: For, he is no Stock, nor muſt degenerate from his kind: And therefore expreſſions of ſorrow, unleſſe they be unſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and unfit, cannot be blamed.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Conſider a man in his corrupted nature; If hee vent his ſinfull paſſions, his raſh anger, his immoderate ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, or if he breake out into ill language, againſt God, and his providence, or the inſtruments which God uſeth to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect us by, if he rage, and fly out againſt men; Is not this Impatience? and not agreeable to our Religion? For it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits not a man to raile on the Devill: <hi>Jude,</hi> verſe 9.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, Conſider him in his Renewed nature, in his Graces of faith, and love, and zeale: Theſe ſhould be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in our afflictions, and appeare more then ordinarily. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9 32. They make a long Narration of their troubles, and deſire God, <hi>not to let it ſeeme a ſmall thing to him.</hi> They would have him to thinke of their Calamities, as they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves thought of them. <hi>Lam.</hi> 1.20. <hi>Behold Oh Lord how I am troubled; my bowels ſwell, my heart is turned within me, I am full of heavineſſe.</hi> An ignorant man would thinke this is Impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, for they are troubled; nay, their bowels ſwell: But if it were no more then;</p>
            <p>Firſt, a deepe apprehenſion of their Captivitie.</p>
            <p>Secondly, a ſorrowfull acknowledgement of their ſinnes, which were the Cauſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, an expreſſion of naturall affections, and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall graces. Then they are not to be blamed; to looſe ſo many bleſſings of all ſorts: The preſence of God in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> The opportunitie of ſacrificing, and doing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111346:7"/> other ſervices: To be baniſhed their Country, and remaine 70. yeares in a ſtrange Land; and not to have been much affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with it: had been groſſe ſtupiditie, and not the grace of Patience.</p>
            <p>The quiet, ſilent temper of ſoule, in a Patient man, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly mentioned: Is meant in regard of Paſſions, not graces, thoſe muſt be put to ſilence, but not theſe. And becauſe it is a hard matter, to maſter our unrulie Paſſions, and not to ſpeake unadviſedly with our lips: Therefore when private in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, or publike occaſions, ſtirre your ſpirits; take along with you, theſe cooling and calming Meditations; which may allay the heate of your diſtempers.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Medita∣tion. </seg>1</label> Conſider that Bleſſings are delayed, and Judgements are inflicted, by a decree in Heaven: and what Evill ſoever befals us, It comes from above; and therefore wee had neede to wait, and be Patient. Did wee fix our thoughts upon God, the author of our Croſſes; we could not be ſo Impatient. <hi>Job,</hi> 5.6. <hi>Affliction ſprings not out of the duſt.</hi> The meaning is:</p>
            <p>Firſt, It comes not from beneath, for Earth and Heaven are oppoſite: and all things come either from one, or other. And what is ſaid of the Duſt, may be applyed to every Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: runne through all particulars; the Sea, the Clouds, the Earth; they would in effect ſay to thee; thy affliction came not from us, nor any other Creature; but it came from God above: <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.53. <hi>From me ſhall ſpoylers come unto her, ſaith the Lord,</hi> and verſe 55. <hi>The Lord hath ſpoyled Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Things that come out of the Duſt of the Earth, do ariſe after a hidden, and unknowne manner, for we do not ſee what is in the Earth: and in this reſpect, afflictions come not out of the Duſt; for men inſtructed in the waies of God, and workes of his providence: know God to be the author of all their Croſſes; <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 39.9, 10, 11. <hi>J am conſumed by the blowe of thine hand, Thou with rebukes doſt correct man, and this makes him ſubmit,</hi> for verſe 9. <hi>J was dumbe, and opened not my mouth, for thou didſt it.</hi> In all Evils, whether they come me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, or immediately from God: a good heart ſaith to him, thou didſt it. Faith beleeves the doctrine of Gods ſpeciall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, which extends to the leaſt matters, much more to the calamities of the Church: And then comes in Patience to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111346:7"/> do her worke; and ſaith, I will not open my mouth againſt it. Faith goes before, and Patience comes after; and they ſtrengthen one another. If Faith be wanting in her Office, Patience cannot make a man hold his peace.<note place="margin">Iſa. 8.21.</note> It is no wonder to heare blinded Atheſts, and prophane Perſons; <hi>curſing their King, and their God, when evill comes upon them, and they know not whence it ariſeth, Jſa.</hi> 47.11.</p>
            <p>That it may not be ſo with us; Reaſon, and argue the point a little further: Either God is the author of thine afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or ſome elſe: If any other, Then it is either with the knowledge of God, or without it, either with his Will, or againſt it: To ſay that any Creature, can bring Evill on the ſervants of God, without his knowledge, or againſt his Will: Is to affirme God to be ignorant, or impotent; both which are blaſphemies: And if it be with his knowledge; and his Will? Then that is granted, that we contend for. It can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand with the Wiſedom, and Love of God; to have his Church puniſhed, otherwiſe then he himſelfe appoints. So that when this is premiſed, God doth whatſoever is done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee: rage, and raile, and be impatient; if thou canſt, if thou dareſt, ſay rather with <hi>David,</hi> thou didſt it: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I held my tongue.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Medita∣tion. </seg>2</label> Conſider, That bleſſings are delayed: and Croſſes are ſent for this end, (among the reſt) to try thy Patience: To ſhew how well thou canſt ſuffer; With what firmeneſſe, and ſtayedneſſe, thou canſt hold on; When calamities, like a ſtorme of Haile fall upon thy head. <hi>Job</hi> was brought upon the ſtage, to ſee how well he could act his part, and proove him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a man of integritie: and alſo confute the Devill, who had told God that he would not hold out, if he were throughly tryed with ſharpe afflictions. And in theſe plundering dayes, wherein very many have great cauſe of complaint, but none for their Impatience: It may be uſefull ſome what more large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to inſiſt:</p>
            <p>Firſt, upon <hi>Jobs</hi> Loſſes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, his Carriage in them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to conſider how farre he may be commended for his Patience, or blamed for his Impatience.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:111346:8"/>
            <p>Firſt, Touching his Loſſes; we finde them to be in his Goods, then in his Children, and next in his owne Perſon. The Devill had full power over him, and dealt malitiouſly, and cunningly; like an Enemy that beſiegeth a Citie, and takes the outworks, then approacheth nearer, he deales at a further diſtance, then comes to handie blows, and grapples with him.</p>
            <p>The firſt loſſe that <hi>Iob</hi> ſuſtained, <hi>was his five hundred yoke of oxen, and five hundred ſhe-aſſes: which all were at once taken away by the Sabeans.</hi> Job 1.15. a great loſſe indeed, yet leſſe then the reſt in ſome reſpect; for after a great evill, a leſſe affects not ſo much: therefore the devill proceeds by degrees, yet this was very great: like the firſt blowe that ſtrikes a man down, and aſtoniſheth him.</p>
            <p>But the ſecond ſeems greater, for fire from heaven, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes his ſeven thouſand ſheep; Such a great number of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and profitable creatures, to be burnt by fire from heaven, is more then the former; and <hi>Iob</hi> might think that God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf did fight againſt him. The firſt was common among the Lacedemonians, and heretofore in England for borderers, and now for plunderers, to come and in a night to bereave a man of his cattell, and if <hi>Iob</hi> think the firſt loſſe by the Sabeans to be but ſuch: the ſecond is by fire from heaven, and is of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nature.</p>
            <p>The third is by the Chaldeans, who came in three bands and took away his three thouſand camels; which was the laſt part of his ſubſtance, and was like the laſt blowe of a wicked murtherer: who finding life in a groaning man, ſtrikes again and diſpatcheth him quite: And every one of theſe three evils, have their ſeverall aggravations. The firſt was great, becauſe it was the firſt: it was ſtrange to him that had lived in plentie, and was encreaſed in goods, and had power to defend himſelf: (<hi>for he was the greateſt man in the Eaſt</hi>) but this man unacquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with croſſes, is robbed and ſpoiled by the Sabeans. And no doubt it did much trouble him, the ſecond was terrible: for it was by fire, a mercileſſe creature. The third is very grievous, both becauſe it fell upon him alreadie wounded, and ſore with other blows: and alſo becauſe it left him nothing at all, and now <hi>Iob</hi> is made as poore as may be: he hath juſt nothing. But
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111346:8"/> his troubles are not near an end, for all his children are ſuddenly ſtruck dead, in the houſe where they were feaſting. And ſtill comes a greater affliction: children part of our ſelves are dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer then our ſubſtance, and goods: and they are all taken away, poſſibly not well prepared for death,<note place="margin">The meſſenger tels <hi>David</hi> all the Kings ſons are not ſlain: but here the ſons &amp; daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Iob</hi> are killed.</note> 
               <hi>it may be they had blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med God in their hearts.</hi> But now <hi>Job</hi> cannot offer any more burnt offerings for them, for neither hath he wherewith to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice: nor are any of his children alive, for whoſe ſake he did offer in former times. His ſervants, who might have reſcued goods, are dead: his ſons and daughters, who might have rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their decayed father, at leaſt might have pitied and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted him, they are likewiſe dead, and <hi>Job</hi> is left alone, mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning more pitifully then <hi>Rachel,</hi> having greater cauſe then ſhe: and needs not refuſe comfort, for none goes about to give it him.</p>
            <p>And let us ſee how it fares with <hi>Job:</hi> in his own perſon, for if that be well, he will be the better able to bear his croſſes. But you ſhall find his bodie full of botches and byles: in ſtead of health, and comelineſſe, he is filled with loathſome diſeaſes: that none can tell how to come near him, and wanting help from others, he is fain to ſcrape himſelf. It ſeems his wife did not afford him any aid, nor did he find ſo much relief as <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> for the dogs lickt his ſores: but they did not <hi>Jobs.</hi> His friends come to mourn with him, but they in ſtead of mitiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his grief, encreaſe it. For they come and wonder, and ſit ſilent, and ſay nothing to him, <hi>for the ſpace of ſeven dayes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> They that could ſay ſo much againſt him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 2.13.</note> might at their coming, have uttered ſome words of comfort to him: but by their ſilence, they do not onely give way to his thoughts, to work upon the object of his own griefs: but they confirm him in the apprehenſion of his own calamitie. And that which is uſually ſaid of ſorrows, that <hi>Ingentes ſtupent leves loquuntur,</hi> is made good by the thoughts of <hi>Job</hi> himſelf: but by the ſilence, and aſtoniſhment of his friends, as we ſee in the ſequell. For immediately he breaks out into paſſion, that before their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing took all patiently. And it is probable that in the time of their ſilence, <hi>Job</hi> was in a ſore conflict, and under a ſtrong temptation: both becauſe he was ſo much altered from that ſweet temper in which he was before: and alſo the word in <hi>Job</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:111346:9"/> 3.2 which is tranſlated [<hi>and Job ſpake</hi>] may beare this ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vaiagnan</hi> of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Pagin.</hi> renders it, <hi>&amp; reſpondit Iob.</hi> It is the ſame word, <hi>Cap.</hi> 6. <hi>ver.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 9.1. where it is tranſlated, <hi>And Job an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Job</hi> anſwered, namely, to ſome diſpute, which he had in his own mind, or rather with the devill, for he having power, and commiſſion from God to aſſault <hi>Job,</hi> would not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre any time, but ſet upon him, and the fitteſt time, was at the coming of his friends, and their ſilence gave him full ſcope. So that we may conceive the devill to have had a ſingle com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate with <hi>Job:</hi> when he began to ſpeak, Chap. 3. and before we ſay any more of <hi>Jobs</hi> trouble, let us now come to his carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age in his affliction. And here in the entrance, we muſt know, that it is our part to conſtrue things, as favourably as we can: becauſe God himſelf commends <hi>Job</hi> for his patience. And know that <hi>Iob</hi> in his firſt bearing of his croſſe, did as admirably well, as was poſſible for any man to do. And that ſpeech uttered, <hi>Iob</hi> 1.21. <hi>The Lord hath given and the Lord hath taken away, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the Name of the Lord,</hi> is as full as could be expreſſed. Many a one would have inſiſted on the one part, the Lord hath taken, and we ſhould have heard quickly what God had taken: and he would have numbred his oxen, and aſſes, and ſheep, and camels, and children, and health, and have aggravated all, and many a bitter complaint would have been that never man was ſo ſpoiled, ſo ruined, ſo dealt withall as he: <hi>Job,</hi> he onely ſaith the Lord hath taken, and acknowledgeth God in his croſſes. Beſides whereas nature would have thought of nothing but loſſes, and we can hardly ſpeak of any thing elſe, <hi>Job</hi> doth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge God in his former gifts, the Lord gave: and not onely ſo, but he bleſſeth God; a rare thing for a man ſo puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo ſuddenly bereaved of all that was dear to him in this world: formerly ſo great, and rich; and ſuddenly ſo poore, and in his povertie, to bleſſe God. And to ſpeak of his croſſes, with ſuch a calme ſpirit, it is ſuch a meaſure of patience, as no meer man ever attained unto more. And what an honour is it, that <hi>Job</hi> made by the malice of Satan, proverbially poore (we ſay as poore as <hi>Job</hi>) yet he is made a pattern of patience; and we have the other proverb, As patient as <hi>Job:</hi> So that when he was moſt poore in eſtate, he was rich in grace. And the holy Ghoſt ſaith of him, in all this <hi>he ſinned not, nor charged God fooliſhly:</hi> this was in the beginning. And for the latter end, upon the ſight of God, he humbled himſelf in duſt and aſhes; and God
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111346:9"/> highly commends him again:<note place="margin">Iob. 40.4, 5.</note> and reſtores him as full an eſtate as he had before; ſo that firſt, and laſt, <hi>Job</hi> is highly to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured. But we find that in the middle ſpace, <hi>Job</hi> uttered di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſpeeches which ſhew ſome diſtemper, and diſturbance of ſpirit. As Chap. 3.1. <hi>He curſed the day of his birth, and he wiſhed that he had gone from the wombe to the grave:</hi> and <hi>complains that life is given to him that is in miſery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He alſo expoſtulates the matter with God, <hi>Am I a whale?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 7.12.</note> 
               <hi>or a ſea that thou ſetteſt a watch over me? Thou turneſt thy ſelf cruelly againſt me: and art enemy to me with the ſtrength of thine hand.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 30 21.</note> 
               <hi>He makes me a mark for his arrow,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 6.4.</note> 
               <hi>and the arrows of the Almightie are within me, and the venome thereof doth drink up my ſpirit: and the terrors of God do fight againſt me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Touching theſe and the like paſſages that we meet with, we may give a threefold anſwer.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Jobs</hi> caſe was a peculiar one, and his ſorrow was greater then any mans that ever we read of, (Chriſts onely excepted) for never man loſt more then he did; and for manner none like him. It was very ſudden, nothing left him but what might the more vex him, one ſervant eſcapes in all the ſlaughters: onely to tell him, leſt if it had not been known, he had not been grieved enough. His wife, ſhe diſdains and ſcorns him, his friends they ſpeak very much againſt him, and their ſpirits were bent againſt him, as appears by the firſt words they utter. <hi>Eliphaz</hi> he begins, <hi>Job</hi> 4.3.4. <hi>Thou haſt inſtructed many, and thy words have upholden him that was falling: but now it is come upon thee, and thou fainteſt, it toucheth thee and thou art troubled: is this thy fear, thy confidence, the uprightneſſe of thy wayes, and thy hope?</hi> In ſtead of cordials, to revive his ſpirit, they cenſure and vex him more. <hi>Bildad,</hi> he is of the ſame ſtrain, <hi>Iob</hi> 8.4. and inſtead of comforting him, upon the death of his children, tells <hi>him they were taken away for their iniquitie.</hi> And <hi>Zophar,</hi> Job 11.2, 3. he is more harſh and rugged in his language: and lets him know peremptorily, that <hi>he being a man of much talke, muſt not be juſtified, and his lies ſhould not make them hold their peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe were the onely friends that <hi>Job</hi> had, and they were miſerable comforters; ſo that put all together, God makes his anger to fall upon <hi>Job:</hi> and he had terrible apprehenſions of his indignation, <hi>Job</hi> 6.4. The devill he aſſaults him in his eſtate,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111346:10"/> and he is undone: his wife, and friends, they oppoſe, and wound him more,<note place="margin">Pſal. 69 20.</note> then if the ſame ſpeeches had been from enemies or ſtrangers; ſo that poore diſtreſſed <hi>Job</hi> ſtands alone, and none pities him; and had he but health of bodie, or if it were a diſeaſe that took away the ſpirit, that he might not go ſo farre in his cogitations, nor think ſo much of his miſery, it were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: but in the extremitie of his grief, he might ſay, <hi>Lam.</hi> 1.12. <hi>Have ye no regard, all ye that paſſe by? ſee if there be any ſorrow like to my ſorrow, which is done unto me, wherewith the Lord hath afflicted me, in the day of his fierce wrath.</hi> And if any object, that thoſe in the captivitie, had greater ſorrows then <hi>Job:</hi> for thoſe words were ſpoken of them, and not him, and therefore they were true onely of them. I anſwer, that they were ſpoken of the whole nation of the Jews, and it is very true, that no king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, or people, were more puniſhed then they: for as God bleſſed them more, ſo when they ſinned, he puniſhed them more then any nation under heaven. <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.12. <hi>under the whole heaven hath not been the like as hath been brought upon Jeruſalem.</hi> And if any reply, that the King of Judah being taken captive: he left more then <hi>Job,</hi> and therefore his ſorrow was greater. I anſwer again, that <hi>Job</hi> in thoſe times, muſt needs be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be as a King, for he was the <hi>greateſt man of the Eaſt;</hi> but in the captivitie, the King had ſome to pitie him, ſome to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend him, he had not ſuch temptations in his ſoul; not ſuch ſores on his bodie: there was ſome ſocietie, ſomewhat to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwage his grief; and he pulled that ſorrow upon himſelf, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belling againſt the King of Babylon, he was foretold and might have been armed: nay by ſubjection, he might have procured a quiet condition. So that we may conclude, <hi>Jobs</hi> ſorrow, to be the greateſt of any mans that ever lived. And then it is no wonder,<note place="margin">Chriſt the Son of God, his ſorrow muſt alwayes be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted.</note> if it work very much upon him; and if you compare the carriage of another man with <hi>Iobs,</hi> unleſſe you find his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction to be as great, you ſpeak not to the purpoſe. And when you read, that <hi>Jonah</hi> was angrie to the death, and <hi>Ieremiah</hi> to curſe the day of his birth: theſe not having neer the like cauſe, you cannot but wonder,<note place="margin">Ier. 20.14, 15, 16, 17, 18.</note> that <hi>Iob</hi> uttered no more paſſion then he did.</p>
            <p n="2">2 And ſecondly, every expreſſion of our grief is not impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, unleſſe it be more then the affliction amounts unto. To
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:111346:10"/> ſpeak much of ſmall croſſes, is not fit: but <hi>Iob</hi> had more then he could utter, and nothing but ſorrow, could have made him ſo pathetically, and eloquently to utter, and ſet out his own caſe; to ſay that God made him a mark for his arrow, was true, and was not impatiencie: unleſſe he ſhould charge God of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, if he had murmured againſt God as the Jews in the wilderneſſe; this had been blame worthy.</p>
            <p n="3">3 But thirdly, we cannot clear <hi>Iob</hi> altogether of being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient: for humane frailtie breaks out, and he having ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more boldly pleaded, and expoſtulated with God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 40.4.</note> doth in the concluſion humble himſelf before him. And it is no wonder, if patience in <hi>Iob</hi> be foyled ſometimes, by the oppoſite corruption. Faith in <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Abraham,</hi> was ſometimes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered by unbelief: and ſo was patience in <hi>Iob:</hi> but grace in the Saints will at length prevail, and be conquerour. And it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent, that <hi>Iob</hi> did ſet his heart to bear his ſorrows, and his frailties God did wink at.</p>
            <p>And to draw towards a Concluſion of this ſecond Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>Conſider; That in this Inſtance of <hi>Job,</hi> all objections that can be framed, againſt the point in hand, may be anſwered.</p>
            <p>As, ſome will object: If my ſorrowes were not ſo very great, I could beare them: But mine are extraordinary, and who can be able, to undergoe ſuch a burthen as I am un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der?</p>
            <p>Againe, others object againſt that particular trouble, which is upon them. If it were immediately from God, I could take it patiently: But I am wronged with unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men; It were better to fall into the hands of God, then to be at the will of malicious men.</p>
            <p>Another comes in with a Complaint, that it is in his body, and particularly inſtanceth in long and tedious ſickneſſes; of this, or that kind: And becauſe he wants health, he cannot but droop, and bee dejected.</p>
            <p>And a fourth makes his Moane; that it is in his ſoul, and he hath often prayed unto God, and his deſires (which are good and religious) are not ſatisfied: And how then can he reſt contented? And if way were given to all Complaints, there would be no end.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:111346:11"/>
            <p>But in a word to anſwer all:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Job</hi> had not one, but all theſe upon him at once: He was afflicted in his ſoule, in his body, in his goods, in his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, in his Wife, in his friends: He was tryed by God, by men, by Sathan; and the greater the Croſſe is, the greater honour hath thy Patience. For Faith moſt ſhines in beleeving things that ſeeme incredible. And Hope, in expecting things improbable: ſo Patience in bearing Croſſes, that appeare in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable. And if thou feare thou canſt not be able to beare, then conſider; that if thy heart be willing, God will take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of that which is good in thee; and not charge thee with thy failings. For you ſhall find, <hi>Job</hi> not challenged for Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience, but contrarily hee is crowned, and chronicled, and many times mentioned in Scripture, for an example of Patience, both in the old and new Teſtament: You heare of <hi>Job,</hi> and God boaſts as it were of <hi>Job,</hi> and it is evident, that what we do, or ſuffer for God: he will make a faire, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable conſtruction of it, and not upbraid us with our fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Medita∣tion. </seg>3</label> A third Meditation mooving unto Patience, is taken from the common ſtate, which every one is in: And there is not a Child of <hi>Adam,</hi> but is borne to ſorrow, and calamitie. And if all have their Croſſes, why ſhould any repine, and murmure? <hi>Iob</hi> 5.7. <hi>Man is borne to trouble, as the ſparkes to fly upward.</hi> As thou art a man, thou muſt be content to beare what is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to man: As thou art a ſinfull man, thou haſt brought troubles on thy ſelf, and thou haſt cauſe to beare <hi>the wrath of the Lord, for thou haſt ſinned againſt him. Micha.</hi> 7. As thou art a good man, thou haſt peculiar troubles, and thou muſt ſhew thy goodneſſe in bearing thy croſſes; ſo that in what relation ſoever thou art, there is cauſe of patience. And here let us rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the caſe, why art thou diſcontented, and troubled above the reſt? why may not all men as well as thou complain? It is as if a great companie of travellers ſhould in their journey meet with foule way, and weather, and all being wet and wearie, one among the reſt ſhould complain, and cry, and keep a ſtirre, that his clothes were ſpoiled, and he is wet through, as if he had wrong, that God had not ſpeciall care of him above the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:111346:11"/> reſt. It is true, that if this man had more weightie and urgent buſineſſe then others, and was hindred more then ordinarie; or ſuſtained more loſſe then others; or were ſingled out alone from others, as <hi>Iob</hi> was, then there might be more ſaid to move pitie to ſuch a one, but no reaſon for his impatience: for God is the ſoveraign Lord of all, and may diſpoſe of every one as he will, and none can juſtly find fault. Unleſſe man did ſuffer more then he deſerves (which he never doth) for his ſin might have procured more ſorrow then he endures; and if God will ſpare others, what is that to thee? But if he be ſpared in one kind, he is exerciſed in another: and this is one fruit of impatience; to think our own croſſes heavier, and other mens lighter then they are.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Medita∣tion. </seg>4</label> 4 Conſider, God takes care for his children; and then eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when they are in trouble: Pitie and bowels of mercie are in God, and in an extraordinarie meaſure, above that which is in the moſt mercifull man. Now any neceſſitie in a ſervant moves our compaſſion, and we afford that to him, which we do not to a ſon. If therefore a ſonne, a deare ſonne were ſick,<note place="margin">Damus agro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanti ſervo quod non da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus filio ſano.</note> if <hi>Joſeph,</hi> or <hi>Benjamin</hi> were ſick, what could <hi>Jacob</hi> deny them? therefore much more God. And this was a comfort to <hi>David</hi> in his trouble, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40 17. <hi>I am poore and needie, yet the Lord thinketh on me.</hi> And he thinks as friends think of ſuch as are dear to them: <hi>Thoughts of peace and not of trouble, to give his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants an end and their hope, Jer.</hi> 29.11. But God thinks of evill men, to obſerve and watch them, and to poure more plagues and judgements on them, for their obſtinacie and rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: to do to them as he did to <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his hoſt. In all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions it hath been the extremitie of grief to the ſervants of God, to be forgotten of God, and in temptation they have ſometimetimes thought they have been forgotten. It was the greateſt part of <hi>Jonah</hi> his ſorrow, that he apprehended <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf caſt out of Gods ſight,</hi> Jonah 2.4. ſo did the Church,<note place="margin">Iſa. 49.14.</note> but her thoughts ſo judging of her eſtate are there gently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved and refuted, for God can no more forget his children afflicted, then <hi>a woman can forget her ſucking child, ver.</hi> 13.15. ſo that from hence we ſee what reaſon we have to be patient, God thinks of thee, either to deliver thee when the fit time is come; or elſe to uphold thee while the burthen lies upon thee.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:111346:12"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Medita∣tion. </seg>5</label> God intends thee no evill but good; thine enemies (like <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephs</hi> brethren) entend no good but evill: the good that God purpoſeth,<note place="margin">Faelix nec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas quae ad meltora com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellit, multi enim qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitate &amp; proſperitate mundo vivunt inſtante ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitate &amp; periculo ad Deum fugiunt.</note> cannot be hindred, the evill they imagined cannot be effected. Good men are aſſured, that all their afflictions ſhall work their good: evill men have no cauſe ſo to think; and we muſt conceive they will work ſome new good, and therefore it ſhall be better with them then if they were not in affliction. For which purpoſe, ſee <hi>Ier.</hi> 24.5. <hi>Like theſe good figs ſo will I acknowledge thoſe that are carried away captive of Iudah, whom I have ſent into the land of the Chaldeans for their good.</hi> If that affliction which was pulled upon them by their diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and rebellion, in which they ſuffered not onely loſſe of their temporall eſtates; but were deprived of Gods ordinances, and wanted the ſpeciall preſence of God, which was annexed to the Temple, and wanted opportunitie to offer ſacrifice to God, and lived a long time among Idolaters: if that affliction be for their good (which is there affirmed to be) then it is eaſie to conclude that <hi>all things work together for good to them that love God. Rom.</hi> 8.28. So that the caſe ſtands with every good man, as with one that is ſick; and if he have a Phyſitian, upon whoſe skill and fidelitie he depends, for what is needfull to be taken for his recoverie, there needs no arguments to perſwade him to be patient: for he readily ſubmits to his directions. So God ſends croſſes, which are his phyſick to purge out thoſe luſts, and corruptions which like ill humours, abound in a peaceable and plentifull eſtate; and we have reaſon to be patient, becauſe he is faithfull, and carefull for our good, and he doth more then any man can do, he gives the phyſick himſelf, he prepares the ingredients, he ſtands by, and ſees the working; that it lie not as dead drugges in the bodie, but he orders, that it work in a fit proportion: neither too much, nor too little, it ſhall not be as Satan will, nor yet as we will, but as God will, our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies would lay too much upon us, and we (if it were in our power) would have too little; therefore God hath wiſely order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our afflictions, which is beſt of all, and therefore let us be patient. But let no evill man, that is not reconciled to God, take this to himſelf; for you read in the ſame Chapter of the ſame calamitie, that it was ſent for the hurt of the obſtinate Jews, <hi>Jer.</hi> 24.9. which are there <hi>compared to the evill figs.</hi> From
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:111346:12"/> both theſe grounds the Chriſtian may ſpeak confidently to his adverſaries, as once <hi>Socrates to Anytus and Melitus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut de tranq. ani.</note> 
               <hi>Interficere me poſſunt, nocere mihi non poſſunt.</hi> They may kill me but cannot hurt me; they may take away my head, but not my crown; my life, but not my hope.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Medita∣tion. </seg>6</label> Another ground of patience is taken from the conſideration of the time to come, when thou art in any affliction, be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that it ſhall be better then now it is; let thy future hopes work thy heart to patience. It ſhall be better, not onely at thy death, and the day of judgement,<note place="margin">Rom. 15 4.</note> which yet may be ſufficient to revive thy heart, but even in this life,<note place="margin">Iam. 5.8.</note> for we have promiſe enough to aſſure, <hi>that the rod of the wicked ſhall not alway reſt on the lot of the righteous: and that the darkeſt night ſhall have a faire morning.</hi> And therefore in all our tribulations, when friends come to viſit us, if the heart be in a right temper, when they ask how we do, we may anſwer, <hi>Well for the preſent, and it will be better hereafter:</hi> and that is the word and motto of a patient man. And it is a ſentence worthy to be written in letters of gold, which whoſoever can ſpeak it and aſſent to it, is a happie man, and ſhall never be hurt by any croſſes that befall him. We may upon this ground challenge the ſtouteſt and ſtrongeſt ſpirit, as once <hi>Iehu</hi> did the rulers of <hi>Samaria, to chuſe the beſt of Ahabs ſons, and to bring out their chariots and horſes, and come out againſt him,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 10. ſo let the wiſeſt and moſt learned man, the braveſt ſpirit, be asked the queſtion in his ſickneſſe, or in his trouble, when the world frowns upon him, whether from any true ground or experience, he is able to ſay that which every poore Chriſtian that is furniſhed with patience can utter, <hi>viz.</hi> that it is well for the preſent, and ſhall be better hereafter. No every one that hath not intereſt in God, nor the power of grace in his heart, doth or may know, that it is ill for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and will be worſe hereafter. And that this is a ſtrong mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to patience, conſider it in a familiar inſtance: ſuppoſe a poore man, readie to be turned out of his cottage, and left to the wide world, imagine ſome Noble-man his friend, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take and preſently begin to build him not onely a better houſe, but a ſtrong ſtately Caſtle; and becauſe it requires time to finiſh it, if he ſhould fret and be impatient, he deſerves to be reproved
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:111346:13"/> and caſt off: Juſt ſo it is with the Church, there were never ſo great bleſſings preparing, as when great afflictions were laid upon Gods people. <hi>Iſrael</hi> groaning under the Egyptian bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, is but in a way of preparation, to go out with jewels, and gold, and great riches. And the like was made good in <hi>Iſaiahs</hi> propheſie, Iſa. 54.11. <hi>O thou afflicted and toſſed with tempeſt, that haſt no comfort, behold I will lay thy ſtones with the Carbuncle, and lay thy foundation with Saphires, I will make thy windows of Agates, and thy gates ſhining ſtones, and thy borders of pleaſant ſtones.</hi> The Church was then afflicted, and like a poore man in a cold cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; and if they could have patience till God had done that which he was about, he would make their condition better. Seeing then that though in affliction <hi>the Church be as a woman forſaken,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 54.6.</note> 
               <hi>yet ſeeing ſhe ſhall be as a royall diademe in the hand of her God,</hi> ſhe hath great reaſon to be patient, Iſa. 62.3.</p>
            <p>And in the preſent troubles of our Land, when it is deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of us, how things go in the Kingdom? We may anſwer: It is well for the preſent; and will be better hereafter. We do not meane it is ſimplie well, but in compariſon of what was heretofore: The bondage we were in was farre greater, and it was a Spirituall ſervitude that did inſlave the ſoules of men. And if we conſider the libertie of the Goſpel now more fully injoyed then in former times: And do eſteem that above our Wealth; we ſhall be eaſilie perſwaded to thinke it better then heretofore: I am ſure, we, the Preachers of the Goſpell have cauſe ſo to thinke. And when they object their great Loſſes, their Sheepe, and Oxen are driven away by Hundreds: we grant they do exceedingly try their Patience. But if they pleaſe to remember, that the like, nay greater numbers of men, were monethlie fetcht into the Eccleſiaſticall Courts, and with troubleſome Journeys, tedious Attendance, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt vexatious ſuites: ſpent more money then theſe Loſſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount unto, they may be brought to beleeve, it is now bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then heretofore: And we have cauſe to render thankes to God, and You his worthie Inſtruments, for this freedome.</p>
            <p>Such as have been whipt with their Scourges, can eaſily aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to this which wee affirme: And our fore-fathers did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the Hope of that we do in part enjoy, and would have parted with great ſumms of Money for the enjoyment there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:111346:13"/> It was with ſome in former times, as with <hi>Joſephus</hi> the <hi>Iew,</hi> who was perſwaded that <hi>Veſpatian</hi> the Emperour ſhould ſet him free out of Priſon: when yet there was no great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability that he ſhould obtaine the Empire: being a man in the Armie, not ſo well knowne, or ſo much honoured, as (if opportunity were offered) to be able to carry it: but ſo it fell out that he obtained his deſire. And divers had a private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion that this Parliament ſhould ſet them free, and it hath prooved anſwerable to their deſire: And the like hope, they conceive for the future: that Your zeale will earneſtly endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to finiſh, and perfect the worke which God hath called You unto: And they daylie pray, that God would crowne Your labours with happie ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Medita∣tion. </seg>7</label> The ſeventh conſideration, let the Church conſider what ſhe looſeth, and how farre ſhe ſuffers, <hi>viz.</hi> the loſſe of ſome things that may be ſpared, and which God will make up in ſome thing elſe as good. If theeves come and take away ſome earthen pots, or pewter, and braſſe, and ſuch like things, and yet carrie away none of your gold and ſilver, no man would cry out that he were undone; becauſe though he looſe ſome of his goods, yet his treaſure remains. Heathens accounted their riches to lie in the vertues of the mind, which made the Phylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher in the taking of the Citie, when his houſe was ranſackt among the reſt, and he loſt all that was found therein; yet he comes out mertily among them that lamented their loſſes,<note place="margin">Non eſt tuum quod fortuna facit tuum. Vincent. ſpec. moral. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi fortuna reliqua deprae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datur omnia at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> adimit habemus ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid in nobis me ipſis tale quod ferre aut agere invitis non poſſit achi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus. Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. de tranquil. ani.</note> and ſaid he had loſt nothing. And he gave this for a reaſon, thoſe things are not mine to be numbred among my goods, which are caſuall and ſubject to fortune; and if a Heathen, much more a Chriſtian man may rejoyce, becauſe his faith and hope of heaven cannot be taken away: his riches lie in Chriſt, his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is laid up in heaven, and no malice can reach that. Nay troubles further our faith and intereſt in Chriſt, for it befalls them that are going to heavenward, as it happens to children, who being ſent of an arrand, if they meet with nuts, or flowers by the way, they loyter, and make no haſte homeward, but if any thing fright them, then they run as faſt as may be. So men in peaceable and quiet conditions, they make not ſuch haſte to heaven-ward, but if adverſity or perſecution befall
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:111346:14"/> them, then they mend their pace, and come and relate all to God their heavenly Father; and in this or ſomewhat elſe he will make up their loſſe, for ſo he hath promiſed, <hi>Zach.</hi> 10.6. <hi>I will have mercy upon the houſe of Iudah and Ioſeph, and they ſhall be as though I had not caſt them off, and I will hear them.</hi> It is pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to men that fear God, to be ſo in affliction as if they were not afflicted; <hi>both becauſe they are not overcome, or forſaken in their trouble.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.8, 9. And alſo to make up their loſſes in the world, God ſhews himſelf more preſent with them at that time, which makes them joyfull; and it is no more, then if a man were in a fair dyning roome, with much companie, and there is ſome ſpeciall friend, whom he loves dearly, that calls him aſide, to ſpeak in private of buſineſſe that neerly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns him: and though he go into a worſe roome yet he is well enough pleaſed. So God cals men out of much companie of friends, out of their houſes and eſtates, and if they looſe that way, yet if he will ſpeak with them, and conferre with them about their peace, and comfort, and ſalvation in another world; this will make them <hi>ſing in priſon, and ſing in the duſt,</hi> and they will be as if they had not been caſt off; and when God reſtores them the bleſſings again, they are fitter to uſe them. So that conſider what thou looſeſt, and then withall conſider what the Churches enemies ſhall ſuffer, and that will make thee pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient: they ſhall endure not any light afflictions, it will fall heavie upon them; they ſhall not be bereaved of ſome leſſer benefits, which they can ſpare: but God will utterly undo them. So he threatens, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.19. in which place the Lord comforts his people, and <hi>promiſeth to gather them that were ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull for the ſolemne aſſemblies.</hi> ver. 18. <hi>And to ſave her that halt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and gather them that were driven out, and to get them praiſe, in every land where they had been put to ſhame.</hi> And for their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, this comes in, and is inſerted, <hi>I will undo all that afflict thee.</hi> He will not onely impoveriſh them, or weaken their power; and in part pull them down that were ſo proud and loftie, but he will undo them: utterly ruine them, that they ſhall never be able to recover their ſtrength and glory again; they ſhall never be able to moleſt his people again. And becauſe a man may be undone in this world, and be brought down and yet not miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable: for God may pitie him, and comfort him, therefore evill
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:111346:14"/> men ſhall be hated of God, and not onely puniſhed openly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men; but a ſecret curſe and plague ſhall conſume them, and that in a fearfull manner, as you have it in <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.12. <hi>This ſhall be the plague of all them that fought againſt Ieruſalem, the Lord will ſmite them that their fleſh ſhall conſume away while they ſtand upon their feet, and their eyes ſhall conſume away in their holes; and their tongue ſhall conſume away in their much.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the proud inſolent adverſaries of Religion would think of it, it would make them more mild and moderate: as the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie wrought upon a rough natured King, ſo it might much more on meaner perſons: <hi>Seſoſtris King of AEgypt, did ride in a golden chariot drawn by foure Kings which he had overcome and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken priſoners, one of them as he was drawing in the chariot, often look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed back, the King of Egypt asked him the reaſon why he looked back; He anſwered that he looked on the wheel, how quickly that part is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and at the bottome, which before was at the top,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Intuens inquit Rotae volubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatem in qua citò ca quae ſumma ſuerant fiunt una; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gito de noſtra fortuna.</note> 
               <hi>which reſembles our condition: we were Kings that ruled men, and now we are forced to draw like horſes: which did ſo daunt the pride of Seſoſtris, thinking it might be his owne caſe, that he freed them from that ſervile work.</hi> If our Egyptian task-maſters had been as wiſe as this Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Tyrant, they would (upon the like hints given them) have deſiſted from their crueltie, before they were enforced: but God reſerved them for their deſerved puniſhment.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Medita∣tion. </seg>8</label> The eight Meditation, No trouble ſhall be too much, or too long; and if we were perſwaded of this, it were no great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be patient. That we may ſee the truth of it conſider, that onely is too much:</p>
            <p n="1">1 That exceeds our deſert, men that are puniſhed more then their faults come too, that's injurious, and they have cauſe to complain: but in this reſpect, who can open his mouth to God? but rather let him acknowledge as it is, <hi>Ezra</hi> 9.13. <hi>Thou haſt puniſhed us leſſe then our iniquities deſerve,</hi> and this may ſtop the mouth of impatience, that it clamour not againſt God.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It ſhall not be too much in regard of our ſtrength, for though God lay burthens on us, yet not beyond our ſtrength, for it would not ſuit to his own ends; that burden which is above our ſtrength is impoſſible to be born, that which requires
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:111346:15"/> a mans full ſtrength, is very difficult, and will lie heavie, and that which is under our power is eaſie: now God will ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion all our afflictions, that they ſhall not break our backs, and therefore he <hi>will correct us in meaſure, Iſa.</hi> 27.7. And let us ſee why men correct ſervants,<note place="margin">Iſa<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 64 9.12.</note> or children, or puniſh enemies above meaſure, and we ſhall find that no ſuch thing can fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Sometimes paſſion ſo farre prevails, that men exceed in their corrections, and go ſo farre that their furie brings lame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and they have cauſe to repent all their dayes of the hurt they have done to others. <hi>And it is given as a direction to men to do nothing in anger,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut. de ira cohibenda.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe they are ſure to offend:</hi> ſay to thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, <hi>If I were not angrie I would correct thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But God by reaſon of the ſimplicitie of his eſſence, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of his nature,<note place="margin">Iſa. 27.4.</note> cannot be troubled with paſſions: <hi>And furie is not in me, ſaith the Lord:</hi> and therefore he is never angry with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a cauſe, or doth his anger exceed the offence; and therefore the puniſhment is never exceſſive.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Ignorance of the fault not judging aright, or ſelf love ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravating the offence done to our ſelves, makes men unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable in their puniſhments: but none of theſe fall upon God, and therefore he cannot erre, in any of his actions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiect.</hi> But hath not God afflicted his ſervants exceedingly, even more then they could undergo, paſſing their ſtrength and abilitie to bear?<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.8.</note> 
               <hi>Pauls trouble in Aſia was above his ſtrength, and he was preſſed out of meaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To which I anſwer, that he met with unreaſonable men who knew no meaſure, and his afflictions were above his ſtrength, as he was a man conſidered by himſelf; but God did more then ordinarily aſſiſt him, and he <hi>was able to do all things through Chriſt that ſtrengthened him, Phil.</hi> 4.13. And in the words before he ſpeaks of being abaſed, and being in want: ſo that by his own ſtrength he could not, but by a derived power from God, he could bear his croſſes. And God hath vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed to a Chriſtian man, more ſtrength then a naturall man, and one can do more then another. And to ſome that are religious, he gives not ſo much ſtrength as to others: but when they are deſigned to extraordinarie labours, and alſo to ſuffer more then ordinarie, then God encreaſeth their power. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.29.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:111346:15"/> 31. <hi>He giveth ſtrength unto him that fainteth, and unto him that hath none, he encreaſeth might; they that wait upon the Lord ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new their ſtrength: they ſhall run and not be wearie, they ſhall walke and not be faint.</hi> It is much to walk and to run the race of Gods commands, it is more to be able to do that, and carrie a heavie burthen; and moſt of all, to do both the former, and not be faint and wearie; and though we can do none of theſe of our ſelves, yet God hath engaged himſelf to enable us to all. So that it is all one, whether our burden be lighter, or our pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſtronger; and ſo long as God proportions our calamities, to our ſtrength, we may ſay he afflicts not too much.</p>
            <p>Neither will he afflict too long, we are apt to cry, how long? and a little time ſeems long: but God that intends our good, muſt take a time anſwerable to his own intentions. Great cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, and dangerous diſeaſes, that have long ſetled upon us are not ſuddenly removed; and though the Phyſitian finds the diſeaſe weakned, and waſted, yet he will not ſuffer his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient to return to his former diet, and imployment; but will ſtill keep him under his directions, to confirm his health, till the humours be ſetled, and his ſtrength fully recovered. And ſo doth God by his ſervants, which makes him to take a longer time for the work; but if nothing elſe hinder, ordinarily the time of ſorrow and affliction is but ſhort: ſometimes called a day, <hi>the evill day,</hi> ſometimes a peece <hi>of a day,</hi> a night,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.13.</note> for <hi>in the morning comes ioy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay but a peece of a night, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 17.14. <hi>At eventyde trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and before the morning he is not:</hi> ſometimes but a moment, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.8. it is there ſaid to be a little while, a moment, and a little ſeaſon; <hi>For a moment in mine anger, I hid my face from thee:</hi> and ve. 7. it is called <hi>a ſmall moment.</hi> And if it be demanded, how this can be true, ſeeing the time of affliction is many times much longer? I anſwer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In all the time there is much intermiſſion, and many calm and quiet times, even during the calamitie: partly by eaſe from the pain and grief that oppreſſeth, and partly becauſe of the joy and ſweet communion with God, ſo that though the croſſe be not removed, but lies many moneths, and yeers, as an Ague that holds a man very long: yet compare the well dayes with the dayes on which he hath his fits, and ſubduct all that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:111346:16"/> time in which he ſleeps, and eats, and is at quiet, there remains but a little behind: And ſo is the caſe with Gods people in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, whereby it appears to be but a little time, a moment.</p>
            <p>And every one may in their own experience, aſſent to this truth, when the affliction is paſt: for when we look back, and ſee what good comes by it, how luſts were purged, or elſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented; graces cheriſhed and encreaſed, bleſſings (which were for a time taken away) being reſtored again are thereby ſweetned, when we look back we can eaſily ſay the affliction was not too long, and it was but want of patience that made us complain.</p>
            <p>But if we conſider eternitie in which we ſhall reap the fruit of our ſufferings, we may eaſily conclude, it is not too long. Shall God vouchſafe eternitie of perfect joy which ſhall not be mixed with the leaſt ſorrow, and ſhall we think much to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure for his ſake a little ſorrow, which is accompanied and ſweetned with unſpeakable joy? God forbid. And therefore if thou find thy impatient heart to murmure at afflictions, or at delayes, cry down all ſuch thoughts, and ſhame thy ſelf for entertaining them.</p>
            <p>And that we may ſee the peculiar comforts of Gods people the more clearly, let us conſider what can be ſaid of evill men, and it is true alſo of them, that their ſorrow ſhall neither be too much, nor too long, but it is in a different ſence, onely in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of their deſert; for God will do them no wrong to lay more in meaſure or continuance then they have deſerved. But he hath no regard to proportion their calamities to their ſtrength and abilitie, nor doth he intend their good, but the glory of his juſtice; and therefore to them there are not the ſame grounds of patience; and if you ſhould viſit one, if he were known to be hated of God, you could hardly bid him be patient and ſpeak good ſence. For what good could ye oppoſe againſt the evill he endures, for he neither in a good cauſe, nor in a good manner, doth ſuffer what is befallen him; nor can he look for comfort, nor expect an end, nor can ye ſpeak to him, as men uſe to do to friends when they are ſick, and bid him be of good cheare, and that there is hope that he ſhall ſhortly come out of trouble, and though it be ſharp, yet it is like it will be ſhort; none of theſe are true if ſpoken to an evill man.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:111346:16"/> For the ſorrows of this world, are but as the leaves in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of the trees, that will fall upon him hereafter, and the great aggravation of his trouble is that God is his enemie, <hi>and will ſhew him no favour,<note place="margin">It is a cutting ſpeech, and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r worſe then their captivity.</note> Jer.</hi> 16.13. to ſome of the Jews that went into captivitie God ſhewed much favour, but others had none at all. Let me go into the darkeſt dungeon, nay into hell it ſelf if God promiſe to ſhew me favour, rather then be ſent to the eaſieſt priſon, or fall into the hands of the mildeſt keeper without his favour. <hi>Joſeph</hi> found favour in priſon, ſo did <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> in the Lyons den, and the three young men in the fierie fornace, and it was eaſie to perſwade them all to be patient, for God did not onely honour them, but aſſiſt them in a ſpeciall manner; that they received much good by their afflictions, and came out with much honour, and God himſelf was glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly made known to many, by the manifeſtation of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie to them. But evill men find no favour at all, if they be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted it is in anger; if the judgement be removed, it is not in mercie and favour to them, and in what condition ſoever they are in, they have no ground of contentment and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>But while I am diſcourſing of patience, leſt by being too long I put you out of patience, therefore I will now turn my ſelf to application.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> For inſtruction, let me inform and adviſe you to take notice of your want, you need patience, and it may be your wiſdom to endeavour the ſupply of your want, elſe you cannot wait upon God in the way of his judgements. He that hath feweſt troubles, and the mildeſt nature, yet hath need of patience; we are ſoon weary of the lighteſt burdens, and ſoon moved with the leaſt injuries: and being once out of tune, we are hardly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to a quiet temper. And though good natures are not ſo ſoon moved, nor doth their anger ſo ſoon turn to ranker and malice againſt an adverſarie, yet nature having no ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall goodneſſe in it, patience muſt be a work of grace or elſe we ſhall not bear much. It hath been queſtioned by ſome,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aqui.</hi> 22. <hi>q.</hi> 136.</note> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a man can have patience <hi>ſive auxilio gratiae,</hi> but Chriſtians that are inſtructed out of the Scriptures, have learned that it is a fruit of the Spirit, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22.</p>
            <p>That we may ſee this more fully, that patience which is
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:111346:17"/> naturall ariſeth from the conſtitution and well tempered hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours in the bodie,<note place="margin">Differences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween naturall patience and the grace of patience.</note> whereby the heat not abounding over much, a man is not proan to choller and paſſion, but hath a command over himſelf, and uſeth his reaſon in ordering of himſelf under his croſſes, and having a ſtout and hardie ſpirit, bears what he cannot decline. But the grace of patience, is from God as well as faith, and requires the power of God to frame the heart to bear adverſitie; and naturall meekneſſe is not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to enable him to ſuffer in a fit manner; yet all naturall abilities may afford matter of thankſgiving, and that in a two fold reſpect.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Though they breed not, nor beget grace, yet where a good diſpoſition is, the ſoul is a plain ſmooth board, whereon a Painter may more eaſily draw a picture: and a harſh crabbed nature, is as a board full of knots, and rugged, whereon the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificer cannot ſo well ſhew his workmanſhip; and though the power of God will ſhew it ſelf whereſoever he intends to make a veſſel of mercie, yet it is with more ado, and will coſt a man the more ſorrow.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Good diſpoſitions ſanctified become more uſefull, and better inſtruments then ordinarie, in that they are more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and amiable to others, and ſo do win more reſpect to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and become more gracefull, and gain more credit to the Goſpel; whereas froward, and haſtie, and paſſionate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, are diſtaſtfull to others, and many times they are ſhunned even for their paſſions, men being too apt to look upon the ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes of others, rather then their graces.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That patience which is naturall will bear ſome evils, but not all that God laies upon him; it may be he can converſe qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly and calmly with friends, with wife and children, and in caſe he be provoked he can bear a great deal, and if any diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence be, he will deſire and embrace reconciliation; but diſgrace and injuries for Religion he cannot endure, and greater trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles he will decline, by yeelding to evill men in evill and unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things, and his good nature will not ſuffer him to contend no not for the faith, but that patience which is ſupernaturall, reſolves to bear not one, but all croſſes, and abides firm and conſtant in his Religion unto the death, and chiefly deſires to be armed, to undergo thoſe trials that fall upon him for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:111346:17"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Naturall Patience is not voluntary, but forced in ſuch things as come from God, as Sickneſſe, and Loſſes, he therefore ſuffers becauſe there is no helpe; but a Religious man doth imbrace, and willingly undergo his burthen, and ſaith in a ſecret diſpute, <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.19. <hi>Woe is me for my hurt, my wound is greivous; but I ſaid it is my greife, and I must beare it. Plaga quae mihi debetur,</hi> as ſome tranſlate it: It is greivous, but I muſt beare it. He concludes out of former reaſonings; that he muſt beare it: God layes a neceſſitie upon him, and he layes a neceſſitie upon himſelf: his heart goes along with God, and he ſaith not onely, I muſt bear it, but I will beare it: <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.9. and both cleares God, and condemnes himſelf, ſaying; <hi>I will beare the wrath of the Lord, becauſe I have ſinned against him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> A Naturall man is not voluntary; unleſſe it be firſt,<note place="margin">Multa in labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus &amp; dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus ſustinent bomines prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ca quae vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioſè diligunt. Auguſt. de pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tien.</note> in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full courſes, and then his inordinate luſts put him upon ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, and diſgraces, and troubles which he willingly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoes: many men have ſuffered ſo much trouble for their luſts, which had it beene for Religion, they had been Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Naturall Patience is ſometimes voluntary, in reference to ſome Temporall good, which a man lookes after: As being wounded in the legge; when it Gangrenes, he may patiently endure the cutting of it off, to ſave his life: And being ſicke, a Naturall man may take bitter Pills to recover his health and the earneſt deſire he hath to live, may make him Patient. But Religion teacheth us willingly to undergoe Calamities, and to take up our Croſſes upon better grounds, and for more excellent ends, then the gaining of a Temporall good. To omitt the grounds which have been handled before, I will a little inſiſt:</p>
            <p>Firſt; In the great Evill which he ſhuns by ſuffering afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he apprehends Gods diſpleaſure the terrours of an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing Conſcience, and the torments of Hell: If he to ſhunne afflictions ſhould yeeld to do any Evill, or ſhould betray the Truth, therefore to make himſelf the more willing, he ſets before his eyes the fearefull caſe of <hi>Judas</hi> betraying his Maſter, and of <hi>Francis Spira,</hi> that to hold his Preferments, ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the knowne Truth in his recantation, and never had
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:111346:18"/> good day all his life; and to ſhun theſe great Evils, he willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffers leſſe: he thinkes a Priſon is not ſo bad as Hell, the threatnings of men, nothing to the frownes of an angry God: the loſſe of all his dignities on earth not to be compared to the loſſe of heaven, and being put to it, that he muſt ſuffer the loſſe of one, he willingly chuſeth to part with the leſſe, <hi>Ferre minora volo ne graviora feram.</hi> So that if ye conſider what he ſhuns, and what he hopes to gain, it is no wonder if he be not onely patient,<note place="margin">Nemo niſi pro eo quod dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctat ſponre ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipit quo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciat. Biel. ex Auguſtino.</note> but joyfull in tribulation. This made Martyrs to run to the ſtake and embrace the flames, and would not accept de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance; and if men did well conſider, they would neither condemne them that are in trouble, nor ſay as <hi>Peter</hi> to <hi>Chriſt, Pitie thy ſelf:</hi> and yeeld rather then run ſuch a hazard.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The patience of a naturall man never brings true com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to his ſoul, he never taſtes of thoſe joyes which God af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords to them that ſuffer in a good cauſe. <hi>Paul and Silas</hi> are as merrie in priſon as ever they were; and <hi>John in Patmos</hi> knows more raviſhing joy then thoſe that lived in the Emperours Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace; but ſuch as ſuffer either for their offences, unleſſe their patience did ſpring from a true root, it is impoſſible the fruit ſhould be good. Faith and patience are coupled together, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.12. and therefore comfort and patience are joyned together, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4. <hi>That we through patience and comfort of the Scriptures might have hope.</hi> And then follows, <hi>the God of patience and conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> which concludes the point in hand, that no man, not the mildeſt man, hath by nature the grace of patience: God is the author of it as well as any other grace, and therefore that every one ſhould endeavour after it, in the uſe of the ſame means by which he looks for every grace.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> The ſecond Uſe is a reproof to all impatient perſons. And here we that reprove others, have need firſt to reprove our ſelves. It was a modeſt expreſſion of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> who being to write of this ſubject, intimates that he was aſhamed to ſpeak, <hi>Ne dicta factis erubeſcant,</hi> leſt his actions ſhould contradict his ſpeeches; and he be aſhamed of his ſayings. Let us all be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for our intemperate language, our unſeemly geſtures, our unfit carriage: we fall ſhort of that quiet, ſilent temper of ſoul before mentioned; our ſpirits are full of bitterneſſe, our mouths are full of complaints: what a ſhame is it to ſea Chriſtian like
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:111346:18"/> 
               <hi>Hercules furens?</hi> or like <hi>Solomons fool.</hi> And if men do not break out ſo inordinately, yet it is too common to hear ſome with <hi>David</hi> crying out, <hi>Oh my ſun Abſolon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 18.33.</note> 
               <hi>would God I had died for the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Abſolon my ſonne.</hi> Or with <hi>Jonah, Oh my gourd,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iona 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>I am not able to endure this heat,</hi> ſeeing <hi>my gourd it taken away, take away my life alſo. Oh theſe daughters in law,</hi> ſaith <hi>Rebecca,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 26.35. Cap. 27.46.</note> 
               <hi>I am weari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of my life becauſe of them.</hi> Others in our dayes ſay theſe are pitifull times; trading is decayed, the treaſure of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is exhauſted, all things are out of frame. In theſe and the like expreſſions, where corruption appears, I am now to ſpeak to it by way of reproof.</p>
            <p>The cauſes of Impatience are,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. The croſſe lies in ſomewhat that is too dear unto us,<note place="margin">Foure cauſes of impatience.</note> and ſelf-love may be the cauſe of this impatience; <hi>Rachel mourns and will not be comforted for her children: Jacob</hi> is impatient <hi>of Benja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mins going out of his ſight;</hi> and the reaſon is, he loved him more then was meet. An when once we are loſt in our affections to any thing, the croſſe proves heavie, and we pull it upon our ſelves. It is juſt with God to puniſh us in that thing we idolize. And if we cannot moderate our affections, we pull a double evill upon our ſelves. 1. To be bereaved of that which is dear unto us. 2. We ſhall not be able to bear the loſſe of it. If we joy too much in any thing, when we looſe it we ſhall mourn too much: and then in ſtead of pitie from friends, we ſhould have a reproof. Impatience diſcovers men, for you ſhall find that in ſome things they can bear it better then in others, and if they be moſt tachie, and peeviſh, when croſſed in matter of profit or pleaſure, or name and reputation: a <hi>Heathen</hi> conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that then they <hi>are covetous, or ambitious, or luxurious.</hi> An impatient man is guiltie of a double fault, one paſt in his irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular affections, an other preſent in his ill carriage to God, or man, in the loſſe of that which is taken from him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Anoth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r cauſe of Impatience is ignorance of God, when we ſee God in a croſſe we ſubmit; but if not, we are perverſe. We ſee a great deal of difference in <hi>David</hi> towards <hi>Shimei,</hi> and <hi>Nabal,</hi> both of them give him ill language, and <hi>Shimei</hi> was worſe then the other, yet he is more patient towards him then <hi>Nabal,</hi> and the reaſon is, he ſaw God more in his reproachfull termes then the other: <hi>God hath bidden him curſe,</hi> ſaith he, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:111346:19"/> therefore he will bear it. If a man meet the King, and know him not, he will not give him due reverence: And if we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge not God in our croſſes, no wonder if we be impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient. It is in this caſe, as with the <hi>owners of the Aſſes colt,</hi> if <hi>you ſay the Lord hath need of him, they will let him go,</hi> ſaith our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our: ſo when we part with our eſtates, if the Lord have need of them, let them go. Let us offer as <hi>Araunah</hi> did, our barnes, and all that is on the barn-floore, our oxen, or any thing we have: but unleſſe we know it is the Lord that requires them, we ſhall hardly ſubmit, and ſcarce then, unleſſe nature be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued by a higher and more powerfull principle.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A third cauſe of impatience, is the diſtemper of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the bodie, for it comes from paſſion, and that is from the paſſive principle in man, where choller abounds, there the ſoul works diſtemperedly: for all actions taſte, and have a ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g of the humour that is predominant; and though paſſions and paſſionate expreſſions are to be aſcribed to the mind, yet all actions elicited, and acted by the bodie, partake of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall temper: It is inbred, and ſetled, and hardly overcome, and ſo it is both a ſin, and a great affliction to them that are ſenſible of it. Paſſions are the feet of the ſoul, they are in the ſenſitive appetite, and when they grow inordinate, they are the diſeaſes of the mind, the depravers of reaſon, the diſturbers of the underſtanding, whereby wiſe men ſpeak nothing, do nothing, like themſelves. It is a weakneſſe to have paſſions, a greater weakneſſe to be conquered by them. Therefore when the people gave too much to the Apoſtles, to take down that opinion,<note place="margin">Act. 14.15.</note> they alledge <hi>they were men ſubiect to like paſſions as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves:</hi> intimating that it is a weakneſſe, and belowe a wiſe man to have paſſions in him. And for concluſion, conſider that when we are commanded,<note place="margin">Luk. 21.19.</note> 
               <hi>to poſſeſſe our ſouls in patience,</hi> it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears that by paſſion, and impatience, we are diſpoſſeſſed of our ſouls, of our underſtanding, of our joy, and comfort, and peace, for that time that paſſion bears ſway. A patient man doth quietly injoy himſelf, his comforts, his friends: but if paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion poſſeſſe thy impatient ſoul, it will play the tyrant, and turn thee out of all:<note place="margin">Mark 5.2, 3.</note> thou art like him that was <hi>poſſeſſed by an evill ſpirit;</hi> and we find t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at he did tear himſelf, ſo impatient perſons wound, and cut, and vex themſelves: and it is ſaid that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:111346:19"/> none could bind him, <hi>ver.</hi> 3.4. rage will break out, and will not be reſtrained. <hi>I would kill a man in mine anger,</hi> ſaith <hi>Lamech,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 42.28.</note> I will go mourning to my grave, if ought but good befall <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamin</hi> by the way, ſaith <hi>Jacob.</hi> When men give way, and let the rains go, their paſſions runne like wilde horſes: in which caſe men are burthenſome to themſelves and others; he that was poſſeſſed of the evill ſpirit was among the tombes; but theſe are among the living, and moleſt and grieve moſt thoſe that are neareſt to them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A fourth cauſe of Impatience is, the croſſe comes ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, and takes us unawares. We break out before we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of it; paſſion ſurprizeth a man, as a thief that robs him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he could make any reſiſtance. It were good we did think beforehand of the evils of the day, of the croſſe occurrents that may fall out in our callings, and families, and occaſions. Collect thy ſpirits, and conſider there may be, and it is like there will be ſome untowardneſſe in ſervants, ſome undutiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in children, ſome unkindneſſe in husband, wife, or friends, arme thy ſelf againſt all, and be prepared. Think with thy ſelf, God could have matched all good husbands and good wives together, and could have given to all good parents, good chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; and faithfull ſervants to the maſters that fear him; he could have put all ſweet diſpoſitions to have laid together, and injoyed a happie neighbourhood: but divine providence hath diſpoſed otherwiſe to try our patience.</p>
            <p>Having gone through the firſt part of the dutie of waiting upon God: I now come to the ſecond,<note place="margin">The Church her hope.</note> which is a cheerfull ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of good. If we were never ſo patient in bearing evill, and yet did not keep up our deſires and affections, we failed in our waiting; for there ought to be a certain and a cheerfull ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of ſuch future good things as God hath promiſed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It muſt be a future good we hope for, not preſent, which we do enjoy alreadie; and it muſt be promiſed, elſe we build without a foundation. Preſumption roves abroad at large, but hope looks for a promiſe.<note place="margin">Objectum ſpei. <hi>1</hi> Proximum. <hi>2</hi> Principale.</note> There is a double object for our hope, one is principall, and that is God himſelf, I hope in God as well as I do beleeve in God: the other is the next object, and that is the promiſe of God. But becauſe the three divine graces (whereof hope is one) are immediately fixed upon God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:111346:20"/> therefore we hope in God promiſing eternall life and all good things in the mean time: hope gives God the honour of his bountie, for it expects the bleſſing included in the promiſe, and faith gives him the honour of his truth; for it credits God in all things ſpoken by him: and love gives him the honour of his goodneſſe. Hope is not mercenarie and yet waits for a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.4.</note> for when God vouchſafeth to give us great and precious promiſes, it were ill in us not to expect the performance of them.</p>
            <p>They that hope and wait, have ſtrong and well ordered de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, ſtrong graces, and ſtrong affections: elſe delay would beat them off, for many of the promiſes of God beare a long date.</p>
            <p>But in hope there is a certain expectation of promiſed bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, and that bears up the ſpirit: hope in God can no more be diſappointed then faith can be deceived, for hope is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of things beleeved, and faith is the ſubſtance or ground of things hoped for:<note place="margin">Heb. 11.1.</note> both of them are in God imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, and both of them are fixed upon promiſes, both begin and end together; and both mutually ſtrengthen one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m</hi> 8.19. <hi>the earneſt expectation of the creature waiteth.</hi> That which is there ſaid of the creature or creation in generall, is true of a godly man, nay it is a lively deſcription of him, for he waits, and he expects, and he is earneſt in his expectation. The word ſignifies ſuch an earneſtneſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> as make a man to thruſt out his head and neck to look towards that place, whence he expects a meſſenger to come with good tydings,<note place="margin">Iudg. 5.28.</note> as the <hi>mother of Siſera looked out of her window, and ſaid, why do the wheels of his chariot tarrie ſo long?</hi> So he that hopes, looks up to heaven, and looks out to all means that may further his deſire, and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and waiteth till God anſwer him. Preſumption and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair are both of them contrary to hope, one hopes inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately, and the other not at all; indeed neither of them hopes, but preſumption ſeems to do it, and looks like the grace, and yet is farre enough from it: both are bad, but the very name of deſpair ſeems more horrid. Preſumption is more common, and kils ten to the others one: Both of them lead to one end, but not by the ſame way. Preſumption goes about, deſpair directly
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:111346:20"/> to condemnation. Preſumption lifts men up as high as heaven,<note place="margin">Aſcendunt ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oelos per pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptionem deſcendunt ad inferos per de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperationem.</note> and then lets them fall as lowe as may be: Deſpair throws them directly down to hell; in neither of them is the earneſt deſire or certain expectation of a hoping man. And as before you had the difference between the grace of patience and naturall mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo here again take notice of the grace of hope, differing from preſumption.</p>
            <p n="1">1. True hope is accompanied with humilitie; paſſion, and preſumption, and pride go together: and patience, and hope,<note place="margin">Lam. 3.28.</note> and humilitie are united; he will lie lowe, <hi>and kiſſe the duſt if there may be hope.</hi> God firſt caſts a man down, and then liſts him up, and ſo we come to hope. But a preſuming man is firſt lifted up, and then caſt down, and his hope vaniſheth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. True hope is induſtrious, but preſumption is lazie; a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous man thinks it an eaſie matter to be religious, and to get to heaven: deſpair judgeth it impoſſible,<note place="margin">1. Iohn.</note> hope conceives it difficult, and therefore labours with all diligence to obtain what he looks after: he that hath this hope purgeth himſelf.</p>
            <p n="3">3. True hope is a ſolid quickning grace, that bears up the ſpirit in evill times: <hi>It is a lively hope,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.3.</note> ſuch as the world wonders at; for whereas nothing but the poſſeſſion of good things will ſatisfie, hope of heaven comforts the heart, and he lives upon it, and eſteemes it a large portion,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.3.5.</note> 
               <hi>He reioyceth under the hope of the glory of God,</hi> for he knows he ſhall not be aſhamed of his hope.</p>
            <p>But evill men that hope after heaven, though God never made them any promiſe of it, nor are prepared and qualified by the work of regeneration; this hope is compared to <hi>a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders web.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. She make a web out of her own bowels,<note place="margin">Iob 8.14.</note> ſo this hope is from their own imagination, it is of their own begetting, it is the fruit of their own brain.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And though the ſpiders web be curiouſly framed, yet it onely catcheth flies: ſo hypocrites look after ceremonies not ſubſtance, and ſuch have the greateſt care of the leaſt matters,<note place="margin">Hypocritae cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram habent maximum de minimis mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam de maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis. Vincent. ſpe. moral.</note> and leaſt regard to the greateſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The ſpider is full of poyſon, and remains in a duſtie, naſty hole, though ſhe work never ſo curiouſly.</p>
            <p n="4">4. She gets to the top of the window as high as ſhe can; and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:111346:21"/> then when ſhe falls, ſhe fals to the bottome, for nothing ſtayes her.</p>
            <p n="5">5. When the beſome comes, ſhe and her webbe are ſwept away, and ſhe is troden under foot: ſo are all preſumptuous hypocrites, in whom there is no work of ſaving grace, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble the ſpider in all theſe particulars. But where a well grounded hope is wrought by the Spirit of God, they are firm, <hi>and their expectation ſhall not be cut off:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 23.18.</note> when the world ſhall be in a confuſion, when earth and heaven ſhall be ſhaken, when evill men ſhall be hopeleſſe,<note place="margin">Ioel 3.16.</note> and helpleſſe, the Lord will be the hope of his people.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The third &amp; laſt caſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded and reſolved.</note>And ſeeing there is in every one that waits upon God both a patient bearing of evill, and an expectation of good: if theſe be ſeverally conſidered, it may be demanded, which of theſe two do moſt try us? whether the preſent evill that is upon us, or the abſence of the good deſired? whether the want of the Reformation promiſed in the ninth verſe, or the evils that fall upon us, till God puniſh and pull down his enemies, mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the text? whether the want of the preſence of Chriſt, or the incumbrances of this world can beſt be born?</p>
            <p>For anſwer hereto we will ſtate it, and then determine it: laying down the effects of both, and compare them together, and hereout will ariſe the concluſion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Evils cauſe pain of bodie, and ſorrow of mind, and they may be ſo violent, as to diſturbe the whole man, in ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as he hath no joy in any thing: but may be wearie of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, wearie of living, wearie of the world, and none can tell the weight of ſuch burthens as many do bear, and have been long exerciſed with in this kind; but you ſhall find the want of things deſired cauſe fainting of the ſpirits,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Prov. 13.12. It muſt not be underſtood <list>
                        <item>1. Of naturall men.</item>
                        <item>2. Not of good men under hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation.</item>
                        <item>3. Not of ſuch as have not ſtrong affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </note> 
               <hi>The deferring of the hope makes the heart ſick.</hi> In every ſickneſſe and pain the heart is not ſick, for it comes to the heart but a little before death, and then it is more dangerous; for then men faint, and go away: and this being worſe then the other, it is more grievous to bear it. But when we ſpeak of heavenly things, you muſt not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it to naturall men, for they have but weak deſires that way, nor muſt we underſtand it of men under the burthen of their ſins, in the time of humiliation, <hi>for a wounded ſpirit who can bear?</hi> but if you ſpeak of men that have ſtrong deſires to ſome
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:111346:21"/> good, and have ſome preſſures by reaſon of ſome evill, or if you underſtand it of religious men, having paſſed through the work of humiliation, it is more eaſie to bear evill, then to wait till the promiſed good be injoyed; but yet you muſt ſuppoſe affections to abound in them, or elſe their deſires are not ſo ſtrong. And the Apoſtle in that text, you <hi>have need of patience,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 10.36.</note> 
               <hi>that after you have done the will of God, you may receive the promiſe:</hi> ſeems plainly to determine the point in hand, that it is more to wait till we receive the promiſe,<note place="margin">Verſ. 34</note> for when he ſpake of <hi>ſpoyling of goods</hi> and thoſe afflictions he ſaid nothing, but when he comes to this, then he tels them they had need of patience, no doubt the other did require patience, but this more then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Evils that fall upon us, or are coming towards us, we flee from them, there is <hi>fuga mali,</hi> and after good things we make haſte; there is <hi>proſecutio boni,</hi> now from the manner of flying from evill, and following after good, we may determine the queſtion, if a man flee from a Bear, or any dangerous beaſt, he makes haſte, till he be gotten a good diſtance from him, and then he goes ſoftly. In purſuit of good things we grow more eager and earneſt, for at firſt we do not fully underſtand and perceive the excellencie of them, till we are well acquainted with the wayes of God, we know not the ſweetneſſe and worth of his love. Therefore diſtinguiſh of the time, at firſt evils com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on us with their full power, do much affect us, and require all the patience we have, but afterwards ſome troubles become more eaſie, as the priſon to him that ſuffers in a good cauſe, becomes as his own houſe, and doth not ſo much perplexe. Good things upon more full knowledge, are more earneſtly longed for, and the deſires encreaſe; and therefore ſuch as are bent upon heaven, and the aſſurance of Gods love, and pardon of ſins by Chriſt, they are compared to hungrie and thirſtie perſons, which muſt have ſomewhat to ſatisfie them, and that preſently, or elſe they die: therefore as at firſt ſome evils do much try our patience, ſo good things at laſt do more put us to it, and it is harder to wait.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Heaven hath more force by an attractive power, to draw our deſires, then Hell hath operation by way of terrour; for faith, and love, and other habits of grace are effectuall in their
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:111346:22"/> kind, and have objects to elicite their power, as well as any naturall affections. Heaven upon a heavenly mind, hath ſuch an influence, that it draws up deſires more ſtrongly then the Sun the moiſture of the earth, and when deſires are ſtrongly ſet, and are in their motion, it is a painfull thing to have them ſtayed. A traveller that minds home, and is drawing home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in his journey, and is detained againſt his will, counts it an uncomfortable condition, and wiſheth often that he were in his houſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 42.1, 2.</note> and ſo did <hi>David, My ſoul panteth after thee, O God: when ſhall I come and appear before God?</hi> The hatred of <hi>Saul</hi> was a great calamitie, but the deſire of Gods preſence in the Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie and having the Kingdom, did work more upon him. The fear of hell troubles not neer ſo much, as the want of heaven.</p>
            <p n="4">4. For the bearing of evill, there are more grounds of pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence then for the enduring of the want of good deſired: for the evill that is upon us,<note place="margin">Si injuriam de poſueris ultor eſt, ſi damnum reſtitutor eſt, ſi dolorem me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious ſi mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem reſuſcita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor eſt. Tertul.</note> may be made up in ſomewhat elſe as good: if a man be ſick, or impoveriſhed, or impriſoned for Religion, there is ſufficient cauſe to reſt contented, and bear it patiently, both becauſe he honours God, and therein he is to rejoyce, and alſo he may have ſomewhat that may be as good as health, or libertie, or wealth, and he may be in better ſtate; but when the ſoul deſires heaven, or the aſſurance of it, and deſires the ſence of Gods love in Chriſt, if he attain not to it, there is nothing can be had equall or near as good; and offer what you will in ſtead of it, it is deſpiſed. If <hi>Jacob</hi> deſiring <hi>Rachel,</hi> cannot be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with <hi>Leah,</hi> much leſſe can the heart be ſatisfied till it have the graces it deſires, and all the good things that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the promiſes, and at laſt the glorious preſence of God in heaven. And it is no ſence to ſay to a man, be patient though God love thee not, and although thy ſins be not forgiven, yet thou may do well enough, this would be odious even to every man; becauſe reaſon and naturall conſcience will tell him, that the want of theſe will make him miſerable. All that could be ſaid is, that though he have not theſe bleſſings as yet, he may in time obtain them, if he wait on God in the uſe of his ordinances.</p>
            <p>And from the forenamed particulars, the heart that is ſet on heavenly things, is ready to breake out, and ſay, I am not able to wait and be patient till I receive the promiſe, my
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:111346:22"/> heart is ready to breake, and many times I thinke it belongs not unto me, what ſhall I do?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> For anſwer; Let us firſt qualifie the matter,<note place="margin">The Church ſicke of Love.</note> aſſwage the griefe, and then (if we can) heale the wound. To aſſwage the paine of this impatient heart, that cannot waite till it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the promiſe: conſider, this Impatience is not ſinfull, nor dangerous, but it ariſeth from the moſt heavenly tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the ſoule, ſtrongly bent to have as ſoone as may be, a large portion of the favour of God in Chriſt, and it is the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie of love, that makes the ſoule reſtleſſe, and if there were not much love, there could not be theſe deſires.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> All Impatience, comes either from neceſſitie, as a hungry man cannot ſtay any time, but muſt have meate preſently, if you tell him, you will a weeke or ſome few dayes hence, bring him meate, he cannot have patience: or Secondly, from Love as a loving wife, whoſe husband is gone into a far Countrey, ſhe longs for his coming home, and takes little joy of any thing, till ſhe ſee him returned; if ſhe did not love him ſo much, ſhe would not be ſo troubled: And ſo is the Church impatient, till Chriſt come to her; which ariſeth from that exceeding love ſhe beares to him, and becauſe love admits of no long delay, therefore it you aske, why the ſoule can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be more patient? I anſwer, becauſe ſhe is ſicke of Love, and ſo the Church is not aſhamed to profeſſe, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.5. And as Chriſt ſpake in another caſe; ſo I may ſpeake in this: This ſickneſſe is not unto death, nay it is the beginning, and a good meaſure of eternall life. Oh! if I knew it were no worſe, it would abate my griefe. For thy ſatisfaction, I will breifly deſcribe what it is to be ſicke of Love; that thereby thou may judge of that impatience that comes from Love.</p>
            <p>The ſoul that hath a more full apprehenſion, and a clearer light, to ſee the admirable excellencies of Jeſus Chriſt, is rapt, and raviſhed with love towards him, and love being the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding affection of the ſoule, is carried towards him in an unreſiſtable manner; for Love <hi>is ſtrong as death,</hi> and will not endure any thing to come betweene it and the object; Love carries the ſoul out of a mans ſelf,<note place="margin">Amor pont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> amantem ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra ſe. Aqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and placeth it upon the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie loved, it makes it to be in two bodies.</p>
            <p>It is pleaſed, and delighted in the object; it feeds it ſelf with
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:111346:23"/> preſent contentment,<note place="margin">Amor eſt ſui pabulum.</note> and hope of future enjoyment; it thinks often of the divine perfections that are in Chriſt; it beholds him in all his works with admiration, eſpecially in that which was his Maſter-peice, our Redemption; It viewes his rare properties of goodneſſe, holineſſe, puritie, meekneſſe, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, &amp;c. And all ſet in the ſweeteſt and moſt amiable diſopſition that ever was; it obſerves with what a Heavenly diſpoſition he converſed among men, how willingly he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed them in the myſteries of ſalvation, how readily he condeſcended to the ignorant and weake, how gracious he was to great offenders when once he ſaw them penitent, how wiſely he anſwered the queſtions of his cavilling adverſaries, and put them all to ſilence: <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.46. Whereupon it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, not onely in point of affection, but Judgement, that he is the cheifeſt among ten thouſand: <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.10.</p>
            <p>And if God ſhould ſhew us his glory, and make all his good to paſſe before us as once he did to <hi>Moſes: Exod.</hi> 33.19. yet we could not thinke well enough of him, for our thoughts could not comprehend his excellency, nor could we love him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his worth, and therefore we cannot erre in our Love: It is no blind doting affection, as for the moſt part is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong friends. The Church may give full ſcope to her affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſhe is ſo farre from longing too much, ſhe can never love enough, but her love being well grounded, ſhe is conſtant, and firmly ſetled, and if ſhe think any thing ſhould ſeparate it would be as death, and delayes is very irkſome, ſhe longs for her Saviour, and knows reaſon for her longing, (which wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men men with child do not) and yet if they be not ſatisfied, they will miſcarrie: ſo the Church in her longing agrees in the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill, but differs in the cauſe. And the Church is ſick, partly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the object of her deſires is ſo glorious, that it overcomes the ſpirit, as the very ſmell of ſtrong water will overcome the brain, and the glorious beams of the ſunne will dazle the eye. So Chriſt the King of glorie, offering himſelf to his Church, doth amaze and overwhelme the ſoul more then <hi>Saul</hi> did <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> by offering him his daughter to wife, and to make him ſon in law to a King. And alſo the want of Chriſt works in the ſoul as a diſeaſe in the bodie. The fears and cares in the Church (which are in every beleeving heart) leſt ſhe ſhould not enjoy
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:111346:23"/> Chriſt, are as the cold fits in an Ague, and by ſuch faintings, ſuch pantings, and ſhort breathing, you may eaſily conclude there is ſickneſſe; and every ſoul in ſuch a caſe diſcovers love, for it cannot long lie hid, and ſuch as are ſick of love, are ſick for Chriſt, and long after him, and languiſh for him, and will never be cured till they enjoy him; and it is no wonder if they be impatient, nay it were not well if it were not ſo. If any that have enjoyed God in his ordinances, and found the ſweetneſſe of them, ſhould be debarred for a yeer or more from the Word and Sacraments, love would make the ſoul impatient of that time, and account it very long, and cry out with <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 42.1, 2. <hi>When ſhall I come and appear before God in Sion?</hi> And if in the leſſe, then it holds in the greater, that the time ſeems long till we enjoy Chriſt. And as the former, ſo this comes from love, and they are ſick of love that find it in themſelves. And it will further appear:</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the ordinarie times of meeting, love will not ſuffer us to ſtay away, unleſſe in caſe of urgent neceſſitie, for as the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that are in love, cannot but go to meet each other, ſo the beleever cannot ſtay at home when occaſions of meeting are offered: where Chriſt is, there ſhe would be, and therefore ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own direction, ſhe goes to the Shepheards tents. <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.7. where ſhe is not ſatisfied with the place, nor the dutie, nor the ordinance, but ſhe muſt injoy Chriſt himſelf, ſhe muſt ſee him, and hear his voice, and her heart is therewith contented, and burns within her, if either he be ſilent, and will not ſpeak, or if he hide himſelf, and will not be ſeen; or do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear frowning, then ſhe is down in her ſpirit, and much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, ſhe mourns ſecretly, and is ſick at heart: ſhe preſently apprehends his anger, and would do any thing to appeaſe him; ſhe would humble her ſoul as lowe as may be, and kiſſe the duſt, if there be hope that he will look kindly again upon her, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.29. and till ſhe ſee the light of his countenance, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his power and glory in the ſanctuarie, as in former times. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.2. and till ſhe find the joyfull ſence and feeling of his loving kindneſſe in her heart, ſhe mourns as a woman forſaken or divorced, takes joy in nothing, is very impatient of his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, but never blames her Saviour, but imputes the cauſe of her ſorrow to her own ill carriage and miſdemeanour; and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:111346:24"/> thereupon ſhe takes up new lamentations, over her old corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and gives not over her confeſſions and prayers, till he again return to her in mercie; which when he pleaſeth to do, ſhe is the more joyfull, by the driving away of her former fears and griefs: and as friends meet more lovingly, and greet more heartily after a time of abſence, ſo do Chriſt and his Church, the Father and his prodigall ſonne, make not more merrie, the Bridegroome and the Bride rejoyce not more, then Chriſt and his Spouſe do upon their renewed amitie, and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In times and occaſions extraordinarie, if ſhe ſees her Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour in any mercie, in any joyes of the ſpirit, or in any delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or in the granting of her requeſts, eſpecially in ſuch things as reſpects her ſoul and ſalvation: ſhe is moved, her blood ſtirs within her, and all the powers of her ſoul are quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and revived, if ſhe hear him ſpeak, not onely in the ſound of words,<note place="margin">Cant. 2.14.</note> but the efficacie of his ſpirit, ſhe cannot ſit ſtill, but riſeth and cries it is the voice of my well-beloved, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.8. And if theſe two ſences, which let in, and let out love, were not exerciſed in ſeeing and hearing Chriſt, ſhe could not with any patience wait for him;<note place="margin">Cap 5.16.</note> 
               <hi>Let me ſee thy countenance, and hear thy voice, for it is ſweet and comely.</hi> But theſe ſtay her heart, and therefore we from hence conclude what ſhe is ſick of. A Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian knows the diſeaſe, and by the operation of his medicines, he ſtill is confirmed in his knowledge; for if hot things do good, then he knows the diſeaſe comes of cold cauſes: ſo if we would know whether we be ſick of love, obſerve what allayes thy grief, and what encreaſeth it, if nothing but the fruition of Chriſt himſelf will cure thee: and ſecondly, nothing but that which is next to fruition, namely, ſeeing and hearing of Chriſt will aſſwage thy diſtreſſed heart, then know thou art ſick of love.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But then it may be thou wilt reply and ſay, this is poore comfort to tell me that I am ſick, I knew that before, and my griefs plainly ſhew it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer: that to know thy particular diſeaſe is more then to know in generall thou art ſick, and it is a skilfull Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian that can diſcover the diſeaſe; and if before or now thou knoweſt this, thou may for ever rejoyce: for wheras many are
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:111346:24"/> ſick for the ſatisfaction of their luſts, as <hi>Ammon</hi> for <hi>Tamar,</hi> thou art ſick for Chriſt, and ſhalt undoubtedly be cured. This diſeaſe ſhews not weakneſſe, but the excellencie of the temper of the ſoul, and being ſo noble a diſpoſition of an heavenly heart, is not properly a diſeaſe, but onely by way of reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance, as ſick perſons longing for ſomewhat, ſo is the ſoul for Chriſt. But as the fruition of the Bridegroome can cure the love ſick Bride, ſo Chriſt onely muſt do it; the Preachers of the Word are but the friends of the Bridegroome, and cannot do it: but let me do a friendly office, I will bring thee before him whom thou loveſt, and put a few words into thy mouth which thou muſt utter, I will frame thee a ſhort Petition which thou muſt thy ſelf deliver.</p>
            <p>O my Saviour, my Joy, my Crown,<note place="margin">The love ſick ſoul breaths out ſome ſuch ejaculations.</note> the top and height of all my hopes, thou haſt raviſhed my ſoul with thy divine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and raiſed my poore lowe ſpirit to an higher pitch then ever by the power of nature it could have attained unto. I did affect ſuch things as pleaſed my eye, and eare, and ſhould have doted to this day upon ſencible objects, but now I ſee that all things under the Sun are meer vanities, fading flowers, and periſhing delights, thou haſt revealed better things unto me, and I ſee by a new light the things that concern my happines; thou haſt ſet before me the joyes of heaven, and haſt ſhewed me the excellency of that eſtate, wherein the ſoul enjoyes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with thee, and now I do condemne all my former ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full delights, and being grown to yeers of underſtanding I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire how ſimple I was when I was a child: but much more do I wonder at the fooliſh delights of my unregeneracie, I find all things that then did poſſeſſe my mind, to be in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of thee, no better then childiſh toyes, I now relinquiſh and renounce them, but my heart is ſtirred with reſtleſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires after thee, and oh how am I pained till I come unto thee? and how am I more unquiet in my thoughts, then when I ſlept ſecurely in my ſins, how is my ſpirit reaching after that which I cannot compaſſe, nothing but thy ſelf, O my Saviour, will ſatisfie, and while I am abſent in the bodie, how ſhall I do to live without thee? eſpecially ſeeing I am in the midſt of ſo many adverſaries, that daily grieve my ſoul, ſometimes I hear men blaſpheming thy bleſſed name, others are breaking out
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:111346:25"/> into odious and diſgracefull ſpeeches againſt thy truth, and the wayes of Religion other fall upon thy people, and offer them all the hardſhip and ill uſage that wit and malice can deviſe, and thy poore Church is as a ſhip upon the Sea in a ſtorme, as a traveller in the wilderneſſe in a miſtie dark day, as all creatures in Winter that are half dead for want of the heat of the Sunne, thy turtle Dove is frighted by every ravening bird, thy flock is expoſed to the rage of each devouring woolfe; and what with fears that do fall upon my trembling heart, and the want of good that my ſpirit is ſet upon, I am reſtleſſe, and know not what to do; tell me, O thou whom my ſoul loves, how I can be patient and wait till thou come unto me, though thou ſhould be as a young Hart, and a Roe upon the mountains, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.17.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Chriſt by his Spirit will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn ſome ſuch anſwer.</note>O my Spouſe, my welbeloved, how am I troubled for thee, how do I grieve with thee, how willingly would I eaſe thee of thy fears and griefs, if I had not other works in hand that muſt not be hindred, I would ſoon deliver thee out of thine enemies hands, but that I purpoſe by thine afflictions to raiſe thee to greater honour, and to bring them to greater ſhame; I will in due time come and wipe away all thy tears, and remove all thy fears, and put thee in poſſeſſion of glory. And for the quieting of thy longing deſires, and ſetling of thy impatient heart, remember, it was honour enough unto thee, that I eſpouſed thee unto me, that I entred into covenant with thee, and am become thine, and thou art mine, I loved thee when thou waſt naked, deformed, and in thy blood, I found thee poore, and have enriched thee; a miſerable captive, and have ranſomed thee; I laid down my life for thee, and let out my own blood to cure thee, thou art dear unto me, and precious in mine eye, thou ſhalt be unto me as the loving Hinde and pleaſant Roe, and I will delight in thy love continually, and that our joy may be full, I will a while defer our marriage, that thou may be made more beautifull and more pleaſing to me, I will remove every ſpot and wrinkle, all thy ſins and the fruits of them both from ſoul and bodie, and think not the meane ſpace too long; but conſider, that there will be time enough for our embracings in another world, eternitie will give thee thy full content. And till then, if enemies defame thee, I will clear
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:111346:25"/> thy innocencie, if they do thee wrong, I will right thee; if thou looſe any thing for my ſake, I will abundantly recompence thee, I will be better unto thee then friends, children, pleaſures, preferments, I will ſtay thee with flagons of wine, and com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ort thee with apples; I will refreſh thee with the beſt dainties that heaven can afford, I will not eſtrange my love from thee, and though thou canſt not enjoy me fully, yet we will ſee one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and daily ſpeak one to another; thou ſhalt be as neer me as is poſſible, I will ſet thee as a ſeal upon my heart,<note place="margin">We may with <hi>Cynicke</hi> light a candle at noon day &amp; ſearch for a man that is ſick of love, and impatient for want of heaven.</note> and a ſignet upon my hand, I will look upon thee and love thee, all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes contained in the Bible, I make over to thee, and becauſe they are thy portion, I have given thee a heart to ſtudie them and peruſe them, and all the good contained in them at my coming I will beſtow on thee: and whereas malefactors never long for the coming of the Judge, but the innocent who hope to be abſolved, therefore I have put it into thy heart to cry, <hi>Come Lord Jeſus, come quickly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
               </label> And now to wind up all in a brief application. He that waits upon God muſt ſtand before him upon theſe two feet, his pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and his hope; and ſuch as want theſe graces cannot attend him: and if there were no other motive then the doing of this ſervice, it might be ſufficient to perſwade us to labour for them. But leaving the particulars, I urge the main dutie of waiting upon God.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is a ſervice wherein all the ſervants of God in all ages are put together, they muſt all draw in this yoke: the Jews waited long for the promiſed Land; and longer for their Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah Old <hi>Jacob</hi> upon his deathbed uttered this ſentence,<note place="margin">Luk. 2.25.</note> 
               <hi>O Lord I have waited for thy ſalvation: Simeon,</hi> and many others <hi>waited for the conſolation in Iſrael.</hi> Some have waited long for health, for employment, for preferment, others have waited for knowledge for pardon, and aſſurance of Gods love; all wait for heaven, and the fruition of God: therefore let none object a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, ſeeing it is a dutie in which all are engaged.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is a dutie highly commended, and ſhall be liberally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded. God is the beſtower of bleſſings, and his wiſdom can find the fitteſt time to give them in; and he that quietly waits, honours God and ſhall not looſe by it:<note place="margin">Iſa. 31.18.</note> Bleſſed is <hi>the man that waits on God.</hi> Every man that prayes and ſeeks cannot wait.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:111346:26"/> We muſt learn ſelf-deniall, elſe the want of bleſſings will make us impatient; the longer we wait, the greater will be our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.<note place="margin">Iſa. 64.4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>It hath not been perceived by the eye, or eare, what things God will give to them that wait for him:</hi> and then it follows, <hi>Thou meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt him that rejoyceth.</hi> God will do great things for ſuch as wait for him, and he will meet them in the mid way: when they think God is not mindfull of them, he is coming upon the way with a bleſſing in his hand. He that waits, is beſt prepared for deliverance when he mentions it not. A haſtie ſuitor moves the King for a reward of his ſervice, but he ſped nere the better; for <hi>Euripides</hi> ſtanding by, and ſaying nothing for himſelf, did by his ſilence obtain that which the other moved for;<note place="margin">Tu dignus es ad accipien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum etiam non po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ens.</note> and when the King gave it, he gave this teſtimonie of him, Thou art worthy to receive it, even becauſe thou doſt not ask it. Such as are afflicted, ſhould pray to be bettered before they be deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: every one now would be glad of quiet times, becauſe of trading and their temporall eſtates, pray to receive good from God by theſe troubles, and wait for thy deliverance.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If we wait not patiently, we run upon our own danger, the husbandman after he hath ſowne his ground, yet waits till his corn be come up,<note place="margin">Lun. 5.7, 8.</note> till it be full ripe, and will not reap before the harveſt. A woman with child deſires to go her full time, though ſhe came her burthen, and treads many a wearie ſtep: yet ſhe would not come before her time, for ſhe knows it would be dangerous to her ſelf and her child. The Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land is now great, and we hope ere long will be delivered of the goodlieſt and faireſt Child that ever ſhe brought forth: and we have need to be put into a poſiture of patience to wait Gods leaſure,<note place="margin">Iſa. 37.3.</note> till he gives ſtrength to bring forth the Child of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation which lies ſtrugling in the wombe.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Pag. 5. lin. 6. for miſts are belowe, read miſts blowe. p. 11. for is this, r. this is impatience.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
